Pull yourself together, Teddy. Pull yourself together.
!خودتو جمع و جور كن تدي !خودتو جمع و جور كن
It's just water.
اين فقط آبه
It's a lot of water.
يه عالمه آب
A lot of...
... يه عالمه
Come on.
يالا
-You okay, boss? -Yeah, I'm fine, I just...
حالت خوبه رييس؟ - ...آره، خوبم، من فقط -
I just can't... Can't stomach the water.
من فقط نميتونم آب رو تحمل كنم
-You're my new partner. -That's right.
تو همكار جديد من هستي؟ - درسته -
Not the best way to meet, with my head halfway down the toilet.
نشد كه خوب بشناسمت ون در طول سفر همش نصف سرم توي كاسه توالت بوده
Doesn't exactly square with "Teddy Daniels, the man, the legend,"
خيلي شبيه "تدي دانيلز" افسانهاي كه بهم فتن، نيستي
-I'll give you that. -The legend?
افسانهاي؟
What the hell you boys smoking over there in Portland, anyway?
شما بهها توي رتلند ه كوفتي دود ميكنين؟
Seattle. I came from the office in Seattle.
سياتل من از يه اداره در سياتل اومدم
How long you been with the Marshals?
ند وقته با مارشالها بودي؟
Four years.
هار سال
So you know how small it is.
ميدوني كه قدر كمه
Sure.
آره
What about you? You got a girl? Married?
تو ي؟ زن داري؟ متاهلي؟
I was.
بودم
She died.
زنم مرده
-Jesus. I don't... -Don't worry about it.
خداي من، رييس، من... من - مهم نيست -
There was a fire at the apartment building while I was at work.
يه آتشسوزي در آارتمونمون وقتي كه سر كار بودم
Four people died.
هار نفر مردند
It was the smoke that got her, not the fire. See, that's important.
مهم اينه كه دود اونو كشت نه آتيش
I'm sorry, boss.
متاسفم
Where are my goddamn cigarettes?
سيار لعنتيم رو كجا ذاشتم؟
Oh, here, have one of mine.
من دارم، بيا از براي من بردار
I could've sworn they were in my jacket before I got on.
قسم ميخورم كه وقتي راه افتاديم ذاشته بودمش توي جيب كتم
Government employees will rob you blind.
احتمالا كارمندهاي دولت ازت كش رفتن
Thanks.
مرسي
They give you a briefing about the institution before you left?
قبل از اينكه راه بيفتي، اطلاعاتي درباره جايي كه ميخوايم بريم، به دست آوردي؟
All I know is it's a mental hospital.
همه يزي كه ميدونم اينه كه يه تيمارستانه
For the criminally insane.
براي مجرمهاي رواني
Well, if it's just folks running around hearing voices
خب اه اونها فقط آدمهايي هستن كه صداهاي عجيبي ميشنون
and chasing after butterflies, they wouldn't need us.
و دنبال روانهها ميدوند فكر ميكنم به ما نيازي نداشته باشن
-Is that where we're headed? -Yep.
اونجاست؟ - آره -
The other side of the island is rock bluffs
اونطرف جزيره ر از صخره است
all the way down to the edge of the water.
از بالا تا زير آب
The dock, it's the only way on or off.
اون اسكله تنها محل ورود و خروج از اونجاست
We'll be casting off as soon as you two are ashore.
ما بعد از اينكه شما رو رسونديم سريع برميرديم
I'd appreciate it if you'd hurry up about it.
خوشحال ميشم اه عجله كنين
-Why? -Storm's coming.
طور؟ - طوفان در راهه -
Never seen a Marshals badge before.
تا حالا نشان مارشالي نديده بودم
I'm Deputy Warden McPherson, gentlemen.
افسر نهبان جانشين مك فرسون"، آقايون"
Welcome to Shutter Island.
به جزيره "شاتر" خوش آمدين
I'll be the one taking you up to Ashecliffe.
من شما رو به "آشكليف" ميبرم
Your boys seem a little on edge, Mr. McPherson.
افرادت بنظر يه كم عصباني هستن، آقاي مك فرسون
Right now, Marshal, we all are.
در حال حاضر مارشال، همه ما عصباني هستيم
Electrified perimeter.
حصار الكتريكي
How can you tell?
از كجا ميدوني؟
I've seen something like it before.
قبلا هم ديده بودم
All right. You gentlemen will be accorded all the help we can give,
بسيار خب، هر كمكي از دستمون بربياد به شما آقايون ميشه
but during your stay, you will obey protocol.
و در زمان اقامت در اينجا از دستورات اينجا يروي ميكنين
Is that understood?
متوجهين؟
Absolutely.
كاملا
The red brick building on your right is Ward A, the male ward.
ساختمون قرمز سمت راست براي بيمارهاي مرد
Ward B, the female ward, is the one on your left.
B ساختمون سمت  براي بيمارهاي زن
Ward C is that building on the bluffs.
C ساختمون اونيه كه بالاي ته است
An old Civil War fort.
در زمان جن، يه قلعه بوده
The most dangerous patients are housed there.
خطرناكترين بيمارها اونجا هستن
Admittance to Ward C is forbidden
ورود به اونجا ممنوعه مر
without the written consent and physical presence
با اجازهنامه رسمي و حضور
of both myself and Dr. Cawley.
"شخص من و دكتر "كاولي
Is that understood?
متوجهين؟
You act like insanity is catching.
جوري رفتار ميكنين انار جنون وايرداره
You are hereby required to surrender your firearms.
در اينجا شما بايد اسلحه هاتون رو تحويل بدين
Mr. McPherson, we are duly appointed federal marshals.
آقاي مك فرسون، ما مارشالهاي ايالتي در حين ماموريت هستيم
We are required to carry our firearms with us at all times.
ما بايد هميشه اسلحه همراهمون باشه
Executive order 31 9 of the Federal Code of Penitentiaries
قانون 319 ايالتي مربوط به بازداشتاهها ميه كه
states that when inside a penitentiary,
وقتي داخل بازداشتاه هستين
the officers of that institution have final authority.
حراست اونجا، تمام مسئوليتها رو بعهده داره
Gentlemen, you will not get through this gate with your firearms.
آقايون به شما اجازه داده نميشه با اسلحههاتون از اين در عبور كنين
Okay. Now that the official stuff's done, come on, boys,
بسيار خب، كارهاي قانوني تموم شد، بياين بريم بهها
what do you say we go find Dr. Cawley?
بنظرتون بهتر نيست بريم و دكتر كاولي رو يدا كنيم
When did she escape? This prisoner?
كِي فرار كرده؟ اون زنداني؟
I'm afraid Dr. Cawley will have to fill you in on the situation. Protocol.
متاسفم، دكتر كاولي وضعيت اينجا رو "براي شما توضيح ميدن. "قوانين
Correctional officers at a mental institution,
افسرهاي تاديبي داخل يه تيمارستان
that's a weird sight, if you don't mind me saying.
يز عجيبيه، اه ناراحت نميشين
McPHERSON: It's the only facility of its kind in the U.S., even the world.
اينجا تنها مركز از اين نوع در آمريكا و حتي در دنياست
We take only the most dangerous, damaged patients,
ما فقط خطرناكترين بيمارها رو قبول ميكنيم
ones no other hospital can manage.
كه دير بيمارستانها از عهدهشون بر نميان
And it's all due to Dr. Cawley.
و همش بخاطر دكتر كاوليه
He's created something really unique here.
اون يه يز منحصر بفرد اينجا درست كرده
It's a hospital for people our society normally considers beyond treatment.
بيمارستاني كه مردم خيال ميكنن ديه درمان شدني نيستند
Top of his class at Johns Hopkins, then Harvard...
اون شارد اول دانشاههاي جان هاكينز و بعد هاروارد بوده
IDs, gentlemen.
آقايون
Show your badges, gentlemen.
كارت شناسايي، آقايون
Dr. Cawley's been consulted numerous times by Scotland Yard,
از دكتر كاولي بارها در OSS، MI6 ،اسكاتلنديارد
-MI5, the OSS... -Why?
مشاوره رفته شده - را؟ -
What do you mean?
منظورت يه؟
What do intelligence agencies want to consult a psychiatrist about?
را سازمانهاي جاسوسي بايد با يه روانزشك مشاوره كنن؟
I guess you'll have to ask him.
فكر كنم بايد از خودش برسين
-Marshal Daniels. -Doctor.
"مارشال "دانيلز - من تد هستم -
Marshal Aule.
"مارشال "آول
Thank you, Deputy Warden. That will be all.
متشكرم افسرنهبان، ميتونين برين - بله، قربان -
Yes, sir. Pleasure, gentlemen.
خوشحال شدم، آقايون
He had a lot to say about you.
اون مطمئنا خيلي يزها داره كه درباره شما به
McPherson's a good man. He believes in the work we do here.
مك فرسون مرد خوبيه به كاري كه اينجا ميكنه اعقاد داره
And what would that be, exactly?
و اين كار دقيقا يه؟
A moral fusion between law and order and clinical care.
يه امتزاج اخلاقي بين قانون و اخلاقيات و توجهات زشكي
CHUCK: Pardon me, Doc. A what between what and what?
ببخشيد دكتر، ارتباط ي بين ي و ي؟
Those paintings are quite accurate.
اين نقاشيها خيلي دقيق هستن
Used to be the kind of patients we deal with here
قبلا اينطوري با بيمارها رفتار ميكردن
were shackled and left in their own filth.
زنجيرشون ميكردن و در كثافت خودشون ولشون ميكردن
They were beaten,
آنقدر ميزدنشون
as if whipping them bloody would drive the psychosis out.
كه حسابي خوني بشن شايد جنونشون برطرف بشه
We drove screws into their brains,
به سرشون ميخ ميزدن
we submerged them in icy water until they lost consciousness
و در آب سرد فرو ميبردن تا از هوش برن
or even drowned.
يا حتي غرق بشن
-And now? -We treat them.
و حالا؟ - ما اونها رو درمان ميكنيم -
Try to heal, try to cure.
سعي ميكنيم درمانشون كنيم خوبشون كنيم
And if that fails, at least we provide them
و اه اين روشها شكست بخوره، حداقلش
with a measure of comfort in their lives. Calm.
زندي آرومي براشون فراهم ميكنيم
These are all violent offenders, right?
اينها همه جنايتكارهاي خشن هستن، درسته؟
I mean, they've hurt people.
به مردم صدمه زدن
-Murdered them in some cases. -In almost all cases, yes.
در بعضي موارد آدمهايي رو كشتن - تقريبا در تمام موارد آدمهايي رو كشتن -
Then, personally, Doctor, I'd have to say,
و شخصا بايد بم دكتر
screw their sense of calm.
لعنت به اين زندي آرومشون
It's my job to treat my patients, not their victims. I'm not here to judge.
كار من رسيدي به بيمارهاست، نه به قربانيهاشون. من در موردشون قضاوت نميكنم
-So this female prisoner... -Patient.
... س اين زنداني زن - "بيمار" -
Excuse me. Patient,
معذرت ميخوام، بيمار
one Rachel Solando, escaped sometime in the last 24 hours.
راشل سولاندو "در 24 ساعت ذشته فرار كرده"
-Last night between 10:00 and midnight. -Is she considered dangerous?
شب ذشته، بين ساعت 10 تا نيمه شب- اون خطرناكه؟ -
You could say that. She killed all three of her children.
ميشه فت اون هر 3 تا بههاش رو كشته
She drowned them in the lake behind her house.
اونها رو تو درياه شت خونهاش غرق كرده
She took them out one by one, held their heads under till they died,
يكي يكي اونها رو برده بيرون، سرشونو زير آب نه داشته تا خفه بشن و بميرن
then she brought them back inside and arranged them around the kitchen table.
بعدش اونها رو برده تو و دور ميز آشزخانه ذاشته و
She ate a meal there before a neighbor dropped by.
،شروع به غذا خوردن كرده قبل از اينكه همسايهها يداشون بشه
And what about the husband?
شوهرش ي؟
He died on the beaches of Normandy. She's a war widow.
"اون مرده، تو ساحل "نرماندي اون يه بيوهي جن بوده
She starved herself when she first came here.
وقتي براي بار اول اومد اينجا اعتصاب غذا كرده بود
She insisted the children weren't dead.
اون اصرار داشت كه بههاش نمردن
Sorry, Doctor. You don't happen to have an aspirin, do you?
ببخشيد دكتر، شما آسيرين دارين؟
-Prone to headaches, Marshal? -Sometimes. But today,
مستعد به سردرد هستين، مارشال - ... بعضي وقتها، اما امروز -
-I'm a little more prone to seasickness. -Ah, dehydration.
بيشتر مستعد به دريازديم - آه، از دست دادن آب بدن -
-You all right, boss? -Yeah.
حالت خوبه رييس؟ - آره -
In that case, you're quite right. The simpler the better.
در اين مورد حق با شماست هر ه سادهتر بهتر
Thanks so much.
خيلي ممنون
Rachel still believes the children are alive.
راشل هنوز فكر ميكنه بههاش زندهان
She also believes this place is her home in the Berkshires.
"فكر ميكنه اينجا خونهاش در "بركشايره
-You're kidding me. -She's never once in two years
شوخي ميكنين - در اين دو سالي كه اينجاست
acknowledged that she's in an institution.
اصلا متوجه نشده كه اينجا يه تيمارستانه
She believes we're all deliverymen, milkmen, postal workers.
اون خيال ميكنه كه همه ما كارر و شير فروش و ستي هستيم
To sustain the delusion that her children never died,
براي اينكه توي اين توهم زنده بودن بههاش بمونه
she's created an elaborate fictional structure,
اون يه دنياي خيالي استادانه ساخته
and she gives us all parts to play in that fiction.
و به همه ما در اين دنياي خيالياش نقشهايي داده
So have you searched the grounds yet?
س شما اينجا رو شتين؟
The warden and his men scoured the island.
زندانبان و افرادش همه جزيره رو شتن
Not a trace.
اما هي ردي ازش يدا نكردن
And what's more disturbing is we don't know how she got out of her room.
يزيه كه بيشتر اذيتم ميكنه اينه كه اون طوري از اتاقش فرار كرده
It was locked from the outside, and the only window is barred.
در اتاقش از شت قفل بوده و تنها نجره اتاقش هم نرده داشته
It's as if she evaporated straight through the walls.
انار آب شده رفته توي زمين
I brought her right back here after group therapy, locked her in,
بعد از جلسه درماني آوردمش اينجا و در رو قفل كردم
came back for midnight rounds, she was gone.
نيمه شب كه براي سركشي اومدم ديدم ناديد شده
Seriously, Doctor, how is it possible that the truth never gets through to her?
دكتر، طور ممكنه اون واقعيت رو نفهميده باشه؟
I mean, she's in a mental institution, right?
منظورم اينه كه اون توي يه تيمارستانه، درسته؟
Seems like something you'd notice from time to time.
مثلا اينجا قراره دايم زيرنظر باشه
How many pairs of shoes are the patients given?
شما به بيمارانتون ند جفت كفش ميدين؟ -
Two pairs.
دو جفت
Sanity's not a choice, Marshal. You can't just choose to get over it.
سلامت رواني يزي نيست كه انتخابش كني، مارشال اينطور نيست كه بخواهي از سش بربياي
So, she left here barefoot?
س اون ابرهنه فرار كرده؟
Come on, Doc, she couldn't get 10 yards in that terrain.
بي خيال دكتر، اون نميتونه 10 متر هم ابرهنه تو اين زمين اينجا راه بره
CAWLEY: Marshal?
مارشال؟
This is definitely Rachel's handwriting.
اين مطمئنا دستخط راشله
I have no idea what the law of four is, though.
نميدونم منظورش از قانون 4 ي بوده
-It's not a psychiatric term? -I'm afraid not.
عبارت روانشناسي نيست؟ - متاسفانه نه -
"Who is 67?"
67كيه؟
Fuck if I know.
!لعنت به من اه بدونم
I have to say that's quite close to my clinical conclusion.
بايد بم اين خيلي شبيه نتيجه زشكي منه
Think it's just random scribblings?
س فكر ميكنين يه نوشته اتفاقيه؟
Oh, no, not at all. Rachel's smart. Brilliant, in fact.
نه، نه، ابدا، راشل باهوشه در واقع خيلي باهوشه
This paper could be important.
اين كاغذ مهمه
Excuse me, Doctor, but we're gonna have to hold on to this.
...ببخشيد دكتر ولي ما بايد اينو نهش داريم
Of course.
البته
CHUCK: And you say she had to come through here?
شما فتين اون بايد از اينجا عبور ميكرده؟
After lights out, the orderlies play cards in here.
بعد از ساعت خاموشي، خدمتكارهاي بيمارستان اينجا ورق بازي ميكردن
Last night, there were seven men sitting at the base of those stairs
ديشب 7 نفر ايين لهها نشسته بودن
playing stud poker.
و ورقبازي ميكردن
Yet somehow, Rachel managed to slip past them.
اما راشل يه جوري تونسته يواشكي از اونجا رد بشه
(ANGUISHED) Why?
را؟
How? She turns invisible?
طوري؟ خودشو نامريي كرده بوده؟
Doctor, we're gonna need access to the personnel files
دكتر، ما ميخوايم به اطلاعات شخصي تمام كاركنان اينجا
of all the medical staff.
دسترسي داشته باشيم
The nurses, the guards, the orderlies, anyone who was working then.
رستارها، نهبانها و خدمتكارها هر كسي كه اينجا كار ميكنه
We'll take your request under consideration.
درخواست شما بررسي ميشه
-(CHUCKLES) -This is not a request, Doctor.
اين يه درخواست نيست، دكتر
This is a federal facility, and a dangerous prisoner...
اين يه كمك به مامورهاي فدرال در مورد يه زنداني خطرناكه
-Patient. -...patient
بيمار - ... بيمار -
has escaped. Now, you will comply or...
... فرار كرده، حتما موافقين كه
All I can say is I'll see what I can do.
تمام يزي كه ميم اينه كه ببينم يكار ميتونم بكنم
Doctor, we're gonna need to speak with the staff. Do you understand?
دكتر، ما بايد با كاركنان اينجا صحبت كنيم متوجهين؟
I'll assemble them in the common room after dinner.
بعد از شام در اتاق ردهمايي جمعشون ميكنم
If you have any further questions,
اه سوال ديهاي دارين
feel free to join the deputy warden in the search.
ميتونين به زندانبان ملحق بشين و جستجو كنين
McPHERSON: It's 11 miles to the nearest land
هفده كيلومتر تا نزديكترين خشكي فاصله است
and the water's freezing.
و آب هم به شدت سرده
Current was strong last night, tide pushing in.
ديشب امواج دريا خيلي شديد بودن جريان آب همه يز رو به داخل خودش ميكشيده
She'd have drowned or been crushed on the rocks,
اه غرق شده باشه يا از صخره سقوط كرده باشه
and her body would have washed back up on shore.
جنازهاش رو آب به ساحل برميردونه
TEDDY: What about those caves down there? Have you checked them?
اون غارهاي اونجا اونها رو شتين؟
No way she could get there.
هي جوري نميتونسته به اونجا بره
The bases of those cliffs are covered in poison ivy,
صخرههاي اونجا وشيده از يكهاي سمي، جلبك و خزه است
live oak, sumac, a thousand plants with thorns as big as my dick.
و هزاران ياه با تيغهايي به بزري آلت من
You said yourself, Marshal, she's got no shoes.
خودت فتي مارشال، اون ابرهنه است
All right, let's check the other side.
!بسيار خب بهها !بياين اونطرف رو برديم
-What's that tower? -It's an old lighthouse.
اون برج يه؟ - يه فانوس دريايي قديمي -
The guards already searched inside it.
نهبانها داخلش رو شتن
What's in there? More patients?
اون تو يه؟ بقيه بيمارها؟
Sewage treatment facility.
دستاههاي فاضلاب اونجان
It's getting dark soon. I'm calling this off for tonight.
به زودي هوا تاريك ميشه براي امروز كافيه
Let's go, boys!
!بريم بهها
TEDDY: You were on watch on the landing, huh?
شما مراقب اينجا بودين، درسته؟ - بله -
Yeah. Couldn't nobody get in or out of their room on that corridor
هيكسي نميتونه از اتاقش بياد بيرون يا بره تو و يا از راهرو رد بشه
without me seeing.
و من نبينمش
Okay, Rachel Solando, who else does she have to pass to get down here?
بسيار خب، راشل سولاندو ديه بايد از كي ميذشته تا برسه اين ايين؟
Me. Glen Miga.
من "لن ميا"
Sir, I didn't see nothing.
قربان، من هيي نديدم
And you were at your post all night?
و تو تمام شب سر ستت بودي؟
Yeah, but I didn't see a thing.
آره ولي من هيي نديدم
Glen.
لن
Tell me the truth.
حقيقت رو بهم بو
I...
... من
I maybe went to the bathroom.
من رفته بودم دستشويي
What? You breached protocol. Christ...
... ي؟ تو قوانين رو زيرا ذاشتي، خداي من
I wasn't gone more than a minute.
من فقط يه دقيقه سر ستم نبودم
All right, look. Let's back up here. Let's all just back up.
بسيار خب، بياين بررديم به عقب، عقبتر از اين
Miss Solando was put in her room for lights out.
خانم سولاندو رو قبل از خاموشي به اتاقش بردن
Does anyone here know what she did before that?
هيكدوم شما ميدونين اون قبلش يكار ميكرده؟
Anyone?
هر كسي؟
-(SNAPPING FINGERS) -Come on, anyone, anyone,
يالا، يه نفر، هر كي، هر كي، هركي
anyone, anyone.
... هر كي، هر كسي
She was in a group therapy session.
اون توي جلسه درماني روهي بوده
Huh. Anything unusual occur?
اونجا اتفاق غيرعادي نيفتاده؟
Define "unusual."
منظورتون از "غيرعادي" يه؟
Excuse me?
ببخشيد؟
This is a mental institution, Marshal, for the criminally insane.
اينجا يه تيمارستانه، مارشال براي جنايتكارهاي رواني
Usual isn't a big part of our day.
اتفاقات معمولي اينجا به ندرت اتفاق ميفته
I will rephrase.
بذار اصلاح كنم
Did anything happen last night during group therapy that was more,
...ديشب در جلسه درماني اتفاقي افتاد كه
let's say, I don't know, memorable than...
... بذار اينطوري بم، بيشتر از
-Normal? -Exactly.
اتفاق عادي؟ - دقيقا -
No. Sorry.
نه، متاسفم
Did Miss Solando say anything during group therapy?
خانم سولاندو يزي در زمان جلسه درماني نفت؟
She was worried about the rain.
اون نران بارون بود
And she hated the food here.
و از غذاي اينجا هم بدش ميومد
-(STAFF LAUGHING) -Complained constantly,
و دائما شكايت مي كرد
last night included.
ديشب هم همينطور
So you were there. Was there a doctor present?
س ... ديشب شما با دكتري اونجا بودين؟
Yes, Dr. Sheehan led the discussion.
دكتر "شيان" مسئول جلسه بود
Dr. Sheehan?
دكتر شيان؟
Yes, he was running the session.
بله. دكتر شيان جلسه رو اداره مي كرد
He's Rachel's primary, the psychiatrist who directly oversees her care.
اون دكتر اصلي راشله دكتري كه مستقيما مسئول مراقبت از اونه
Huh.
آهان
TEDDY: We're gonna need to speak with Dr. Sheehan.
لازمه كه ما با دكتر شيان صحبت كنيم
I'm afraid that won't be possible. He left on the ferry this morning.
متاسفم. اين كار رو نمي تونين بكنين ايشون امروز صبح با كشتي از اينجا رفتن
His vacation was already planned. He'd been putting it off too long.
مرخصيشون از قبل برنامه ريزي شده بود اون كلي تعطيلاتش رو عقب انداخته بود
You're in a state of lockdown, a dangerous patient has escaped,
... شما يه قدم با زنداني شدن فاصله دارين يك مريض خطرناك فرار كرده
and you let her primary doctor leave on vacation?
و شما به دكتر اصلي اون اجازه داديد بره تعطيلات؟
Well, of course. He's a doctor.
!البته! اون يه دكتره
Do you have the phone number for where he's gone?
شما شماره تلفن جايي كه رفته رو دارين؟
Hello? Hello?
الو ... الو؟
Hello? Anybody there?
الو؟ كسي اونجا نيست؟
I'm sorry, sir, but it's all down. All the lines.
معذرت مي خوام آقا اما همه خط ها قطعن
The storm's hitting the mainland like a hammer.
طوفان شديدي در اونجا اومده
If you get it working, come find me immediately.
اه تونستي تماس بيري سريع منو خبر كن
The marshals need to make an important call.
مارشالها بايد تماس مهمي بيرن
Yes, sir.
بله آقا
Hello? Hello?
الو؟
CAWLEY: I'm afraid I have evening rounds in the wards,
متاسفانه من بايد به سركشي ساختونها برم
but I'll be having drinks and a cigar at my house around 9:00,
اما ساعت 9 براي مشروب و سيار برميردم خونم
if you'd care to drop by.
اه خواستين سري بزنين
Good. We can talk then, right?
خب س اون موقع حرف مي زنيم
We have been talking, Marshal.
ما حرفهامون رو زديم مارشال
Gotta say, I'm thinking I got in the wrong line of public service.
بايد بم فكر ميكنم جاي اشتباهي اومدم
It is a little overwhelming. It was constructed during the Civil War,
يه كم زيادي مستحكمه اينجا رو در زمان جنهاي داخلي ساختن
the same time as the military fort housing Ward C.
C همون زماني كه نيروهاي ارتش در ساختمون ساكن شدن
This is the original commander's quarters.
اينجا مركز فرماندهي بوده
When Uncle Sam got the bill, the commander was court-martialed.
وقتي رييس جمهور فهميد فرمانده اينجا داداهي شد
I can see why.
ميبينم را
Nice music. Who is that? Brahms?
آهن قشنيه. مال كيه؟ برامز؟
No.
نه
-It's Mahler. -NAEHRING: Quite right, Marshal.
ماهلر - درسته مارشال -
CAWLEY: Forgive me, gentlemen. My colleague, Dr Jeremiah Naehring.
"آقايون، همكار من دكتر "جرمي نرين
Quartet for Piano and Strings in A minor.
قطعه 4نفري براي يانو وسازهاي زهي در آ مينور
Your poison, gentlemen?
سم شما آقايون؟
-Rye, if you got it. -Soda and ice, please. Thanks.
ندم سياه، اه متوجه شده باشين - ليموناد خنك، لطفا، متشكرم -
Oh? You don't indulge in alcohol? I'm surprised.
اوه، شما با مشروبات الكلي موافق نيستين؟ تعجب كردم
Isn't it common for men in your profession to imbibe?
براي آدمهاي تو كار شما اين عادي نيست كه نوشيدني بخورن؟
Common enough. And yours?
آره، معموله شما طور؟
I'm sorry?
ببخشيد؟
-Your profession, Doctor. Psychiatry. -Yes.
حرفه زشكي، روانزشكي - بله -
I always heard it was overrun with boozers and drunks.
شنيده بودم ر از آدمهاي مست و دايم الخمره
Not that I've noticed.
نه اونطوري كه من متوجه شدم
What's that? Iced tea in your glass, there?
اين يه؟ اي سرده كه توي ليوانتونه؟
Excellent, Marshal. You have outstanding defense mechanisms.
آفرين مارشال. شما مكانيزم دفاعي خوبي دارين
You must be quite adept at interrogations, hmm?
شما بايد حسابي به بازجويي عادت كرده باشين
Men like you are my specialty, you know?
افرادي مثل تو ... در تخصص من هستن
Men of violence.
مردم خشونت
Now that's a hell of an assumption to make.
فرض وحشتناكيه
No assumption. No, not at all. You misunderstand me.
فرضي در كار نيست، اصلا. شما درست نفهميدين
I said you are men of violence.
من فتم شما مردهاي خشونت هستين
I'm not accusing you of being violent men.
شما رو متهم نكردم كه خشن هستين
That's quite different.
اين فرق داره
No, please. Please. Edify us, Doctor.
خواهش ميكنم ما رو روشن كنين، دكتر
You both served overseas, huh?
هردوي شما در جنهاي خارجي شركت كردين
It's not much of a stretch, Doc.
خيلي كار سختي نبوده دكتر
For all you know, we were both paper pushers over there.
همونطور كه ميدونين ما اونجا فقط كارهاي دفتري ميكرديم
No, you were not.
نه اينطور نيست
Since the schoolyard,
از زمان مدرسه
neither of you has ever walked away from a physical conflict.
شرط ميبيندم كه هيكدوم شما از خير يه دعوا هم نذشتين
No, no, not because you enjoy it,
نه اينكه از دعوا خوشتون ميومده
but because retreat isn't something you consider an option.
اما براي شما يزي به اسم عقبنشيني وجود نداشته
We weren't raised to run, Doc.
ما براي فرار كردن تربيت نشديم دكتر
Ah! Yes. "Raised."
آه، آره... تربيت شدن
And who raised you, Marshal?
و كي شما رو تربيت كرده، مارشال؟
Me?
من؟
-Wolves. -Ah!
رها - آه -
Very impressive defense mechanisms.
سيستم دفاعي خيلي موثر
NAEHRING: Do you believe in God, Marshal?
شما به خدا اعتقاد داري، مارشال؟
No, I'm quite serious.
صحبتم كاملا جديه
You ever seen a death camp, Doctor?
تا حالا يه ادواه جنازه ديدين؟
Huh?
ها؟
(CONTINUES IN GERMAN)
من ديدم، من اونجا بودم "براي آزادي "دااو
His English really is very good.
انليسي شما خيلي خوبه، عاليه
You hit the consonants a tad hard, though.
انليسي شما خيلي خوبه مثل بهها تلفظ ميكنين
You're a German?
شما آلماني هستين؟
Is legal immigration a crime, Marshal?
مهاجرت قانوني جرمه، مارشال؟
Oh, I don't know, Doctor. You tell us.
نميدونم دكتر، شما بين
Now, listen. We're gonna need those files on Sheehan
ما به روندههاي شيهان
and the rest of the staff as well.
و بقيه كاركنان اينجا نياز داريم
No personnel files will be released to you. Period.
اون روندهها به شما داده نميشه !تمام
-(FIRMLY) We're gonna need those files. -Out of the question.
ما به اون اطلاعات نياز داريم - اونها به شما ربطي ندارن -
-Bullshit, out of the question! Bullshit! -(GLASS SHATTERING)
!مزخرف نو، اين يه درخواست نيست، مزخرف نو
Just who the hell's in charge here, anyway, huh?
كي اينجا مسئوله، هان؟
Dr. Naehring acts as liaison to our Board of Overseers.
دكتر ناهرين رابط ما با مسئولين در خارج از اينجاست
He relayed your request, and it's been refused.
اون درخواست شما رو فرستاد و رد شد
Refused? They don't have the authority to refuse, and neither do you, sir.
رد شد؟ اونها حق نين كاري رو ندارن !شما هم نين حقي ندارين، آقا
Marshal, continue your investigation and we'll do all we can to help.
مارشال، تحقيقاتتون رو ادامه بدين ما هم هر كمكي بتونيم بهتون ميكنيم
This investigation is over.
اين تحقيقات تموم شدست
We're gonna file our reports and we're gonna hand it over to...
... ما يه زارش مينويسيم و ميديم به
-CHUCK: Hoover's boys. -Hoover's boys. That's right.
افراد "هوور"ه - درسته، افراد هوور -
We'll be taking the ferry back in the morning. Come on, Chuck.
و فردا با اولين كشتي از اينجا ميريم بجنب اك
McPHERSON: Nice night.
شب خوبيه
You'll be bunking in the orderlies' quarters.
شب رو در قسمت خدمتكارها ميمونين
Hey, boss. We really packing it in?
هي رييس واقعا بايد وسايلمون رو جمع كنيم؟
Why?
طور؟
I guess... I don't know, I just never really quit anything before.
نميدونم... من فقط ... قبلا هي روندهاي رو ول نكرده بودم
We haven't heard the truth once yet, Chuck.
ما هنوز حقيقت رو نشنيديم، اك
Listen, Rachel Solando didn't slip out of a locked cell, barefoot,
راشل سولاندو بدون كمك كسي ابرهنه از يه اتاقي كه درش قفل بوده
without any help.
فرار نكرده
I think she had a lot of help.
فكر ميكنم بهش حسابي كمك شده
Maybe Cawley's sitting up in his mansion right now
شايد الان كاولي توي عمارتش نشسته و
rethinking his whole attitude.
داره به كارهاش فكر ميكنه
-Maybe, in the morning, we'll be... -You're bluffing?
شايد فردا صبح - تو بهشون بلوف زدي؟ -
I didn't say that.
من اينو نفتم
I found a whole stack of these, Teddy.
يه عالمه از اينها اون شت يدا كردم، تدي
Jesus, are you ever sober anymore?
خداي من، شده كه تو مست نباشي؟
I killed a lot of people in the war.
من توي جن كلي آدم كشتم
Is that why you drink?
به اين خاطر از اينها ميخوري؟
Are you real?
تو واقعي هستي؟
No.
نه
She's still here.
اون هنوز اينجاست
Who?
كي؟
Rachel?
راشل
She never left.
اون هيوقت اينجا رو ترك نكرده
Remember when we stayed in the cabin in the summer, Teddy?
يادته توي كلبه كنار درياه بوديم؟
We were so happy.
... خيلي خوشحال بوديم
She's here.
اون اينجاست
You can't leave.
تو نميتوني از اينجا بري
I'm not gonna leave.
من از اينجا نميرم
I love you so much.
خيلي دوستت دارم
I'm just bones in a box, Teddy.
من فقط استخونهاي توي يه جعبه هستم، تدي
No.
نه
I am.
را هستم
You have to wake up.
تو بايد بيدار شي
I won't go.
من نميرم
You're here.
تو اينجا هستي
I'm not. You have to face that.
نه نيستم تو بايد با هاش روبرو بشي
But she is.
اون زن اينجاست
So is he.
و اون مرد هم هست
Who?
كي؟
Laeddis.
"ليديس"
-I have to go. -No.
من بايد برم
No, please. Please. I need to hold on to you.
... نه! خواهش ميكنم
-Just a little bit longer, please. -(GROANING) Oh, God, Teddy.
... فقط يه كم بيشتر - ...اوه، تدي -
You have to let me go.
بايد بذاري من برم
I can't.
نميتونم
Ain't gonna be no ferry in this shit.
در اين وضعيت هي كشتي به اينجا نمياد
Doctor!
دكتر
Doctor, Doctor.
!دكتر، دكتر
We need to interview the patients who were in Rachel's group therapy session.
ما بايد با بيمارهايي كه اون شب در جلسه درماني با راشل بودن، صحبت كنيم
I thought your investigation was finished.
فكر ميكردم تحقيقات شما تموم شده
Well, it's not like we could take the ferry.
بنظر نمياد كه بتونيم از اينجا بريم
Now, was Rachel receiving any other treatments for her illnesses?
و آيا راشل درمان ديري براي بيمارياش داشت؟
Do you know the state of the mental health field these days, gentlemen?
شماها ميدونين كه وضعيت سلامتي روان اين روزها طوريه، آقايون؟
No, not a clue, Doctor.
نه، ما كه دكتر نيستيم
War.
جن
The old school believes in surgical intervention.
قديميها به عمل جراحي اعتقاد دارن
Psychosurgery.
عمل جراحي
Procedures like the transorbital lobotomy.
عملي كه در آن قسمتي از مغز رو بر ميدارن
Some say the patients become reasonable, docile.
بعضيها مين اينطوري بيمارها عقلشون سرجاش مياد
Others say they become zombies.
ديران مين اونها تبديل به "مردههاي متحرك" ميشن
-And the new school? -Psychopharmacology.
و جديدها؟ - روان درماني -
A new drug has just been approved called Thorazine,
اخيرا يه داروي جديد آزمايش شده به اسم تورازين
which relaxes psychotic patients, you could say tames them.
كه به بيمارهاي رواني آرامش ميده يه جورايي اونها رو آروم ميكنه
And which school are you, Doctor?
و شما در كدوم طرفي هستين، دكتر؟ - من؟ -
Me? I have this radical idea that if you treat a patient with respect,
من اين اصل رو در نظر دارم كه ار با احترام با بيمار رفتار كنيم
listen to him, try and understand, you just might reach him.
بهشون وش بديم. سعي كني كه دركشون كني اونوقت ممكنه بهشون برسي
Come on, Marge. It's okay.
مسئله اي نيست
-These patients, huh? -Even these.
!اين بيمارها؟ - منظورم اينه كه حتي اينها -
What should be a last resort is becoming a first response.
آخرين يزي كه امتحان ميكنيم اولين نتيجه رو ميده
Give them a pill, put them in a corner, it all goes away.
بهشون دوا بدي و بذاريشون يه كناري و همه يز از بين ميره
Rachel Solando was on a combination of drugs
به راشل سولاندو تركيبي از داروها داده ميشد
meant to keep her from becoming violent,
كه مانع از رفتار خشونت آميز اون بشه
but it was only intermittently effective.
ولي اثر اون دورهاي بود
The greatest obstacle to her recovery
بزرترين مانع در درمان اون اين بود كه
was her refusal to face what she had done.
اون كاري كه كرده بود را انكار ميكرد
"Was."
"ميكرد"
Is there a reason you keep referring to your patient in the past tense, Doctor?
دليل خاصي دارين كه در مورد بيمارتون از افعال ذشته استفاده ميكنين؟
Look outside, Marshal. Why do you think?
بيرون رو ناه كن مارشال ه فكري ميكنين؟
Next up is Peter Breene.
"بعدي "يتر برينه
Assaulted his father's nurse with broken glass.
كه به رستار درش با يه بطري شكسته حمله كرده
Nurse survived, but her face is permanently disfigured.
رستار زنده موند ولي صورتش تا ابد از ريخت افتاده
I can't wait.
نميتونم صبر كنم
She'd smile at me. She was so sweet, but you could see it in her eyes.
اون به من لبخند ميزد. اون خيلي جذاب بود اما من ميتونستم از شماش بخونم
She liked to be naked, to suck cock.
اون دوست داشت لخت بشه ... اون دوست داشت
Okay, Mr. Breene.
بسيار خب، آقاي برين
And then she asked me if she can have a glass of water?
بعدش رسيد كه ميتونه يه ليوان آب برداره
Alone, in the kitchen, like that's no big deal?
تنها توي آشزخونه؟ اين كار بزري نبوده؟
-Well, why was that a big deal? -It was obvious.
را اين يه كار بزر بوده؟ - خب معلومه -
She wanted me to pull out my thing so that she could laugh at it.
اون ميخواست من يزم رو دربيارم تا بهش بخنده
Mr. Breene.
آقاي برين
We need to ask you some questions, okay?
ما بايد ند تا سوال ازتون برسم، خب؟
When I cut her, she screamed.
... وقتي صورتش رو بريدم جيغ زد
But (SNORTS) she scared me.
... اما اون منو ترسوند
-What did she expect? -TEDDY: Interesting.
ه انتظاري داشت؟ - جالبه -
But we're here to talk about Rachel Solando, okay?
اما ما اينجا هستيم كه درباره راشل سولاندو صحبت كنيم، خب؟
Rachel Solando. Do you...
... راشل سولاندو
Do you know that she drowned her own kids?
ميدونستين اون بههاي خودش رو غرق كرده؟
She drowned her kids!
اون بههاي خودش رو غرق كرده
This is... This is a sick fucking world we live in, I'll tell you that.
اين دنياي مريض لعنتي كه توش زندي ميكنيم
But you know what? They should be gassed.
ميدونين يه؟ همه اونها رو بايد با از كشت
All of them. The retards, the killers, the niggers.
همشون رو قاتلها،اون كاكا سياهها
You kill your own kid, gas the bitch.
به خودت رو بكشي اون هرزه رو بايد با از كشت
Could you stop that?
لطفا... بس كن
-That nurse... -Please, stop that.
اون رستار؟ - خواهش ميكنم بس كن
That nurse, maybe she had kids, huh?
اون رستار ممكن بود به داشته باشه
A husband.
شوهر
Just trying to make ends meet,
فقط ميخواسته درآمدي داشته باشه
lead a normal life.
كه يه زندي عادي داشته باشه
It says in your file that
و توي روندهات آمده كه
you tore her face off. Didn't you?
تو صورتش رو خط خطي كردي، مه نه
Congratulations.
تبريك ميم
No more normal for her, not ever again. No.
ديه زندي عادي نه، ديه هيوقت
Do you know what she was afraid of?
ميدوني اون از ي ترسيده بوده؟
You.
از تو
(LOUDLY) Could you stop that? Please?
ميشه بس كني، خواهش ميكنم
Stop that!
!بس كن
Please! Stop!
!خواهش ميكنم، بس كن
Do you know a patient named Andrew Laeddis? Do you?
بيماري به اسم آندرو ليديس ميشناسي؟
No! No.
!نه! نه
-Boss. What's up? -Fine.
رييس, ه خبره؟ - مشکلي نيست -
-I wanna go back. I wanna go. -Peter!
من ميخوام برردم. من ميخوام برم - يتر -
Come on! I got him. Peter! Peter! Hey, Peter!
!دارمش, يتر! يتر !هي يتر
PETER: Go back. I wanna go back. TREY: Come on, Peter.
بررد, ميخوام برردم يتر
-I don't wanna see him. -Easy now.
نميخوام ببينمش - آروم باش -
-I don't wanna see him anymore. -It's okay. It's all right.
نميخوام ديه ببينمش - باشه، باشه -
Oh, I'll never get out of here. I'm not sure that I should.
خب من هيوقت از اينجا بيرون نميرم نبايد هم برم
Excuse me for saying this, Miss Kearns...
... معذرت ميخوام كه اينو ميم ... دوشيزه كرنز
-Mrs. -Mrs. Kearns.
خانم - خانم كرنز -
But you seem quite normal.
... شما بنظر بنظر طبيعي مياين
I mean, in comparison to the other patients here.
در مقايسه با دير بيمارهاي اينجا
Well, I have my dark days. I suppose everybody does.
خب من روزهاي تاريك خودم رو داشتم فكر ميكنم همه داشتن
The difference is most people don't kill their husbands with an ax.
فرقش اينه كه اكثر مردم، شوهرشون رو با تبر نميكشن
Ah.
آه
Although, personally, I think if a man beats you
اره شخصا معتقدم اه يه مردي كتكتون بزنه و با
and fucks half the women he sees, and no one will help you,
نصف زنهايي كه ميبينه همبستر بشه و هيكسي كمكتون كنه
axing him isn't the least understandable thing you could do.
كشتنش با تبر حداقل يز قابل دركيه كه ميتونين انجام بدين
Maybe you shouldn't get out.
شايد نبايد از اينجا برين بيرون
What would I do if I did? I don't know the world anymore.
اه برم يكار كنم؟ من ديه دنيا رو نميشناسم
They say there are bombs that can reduce whole cities to ash.
مين الان بمبهايي هست كه ميتونه يه شهر رو به خاكستر تبديل كنه
And what do you call them, televisions, voices and faces coming from a box.
و بهش ي مين تلويزيون" .صدا و تصوير از توي يه جعبه در مياد"
(CHUCKLES) I hear enough voices already.
من الانم به اندازه كافي صدا ميشنوم
What can you tell us about Rachel?
درباره راشل ي ميتونين بهمون بين؟
Um...
... آ
Not much. She keeps to herself.
يز زيادي نيست اون ... اون همش توي خودش بود
She believed her kids were alive.
اون مطمئن بود كه بههاش زندهان
She thought she was still living in the Berkshires,
فكر ميكرد كه هنوز توي بركشاير زندي ميكنه
and we were all her neighbors, the milkmen, postmen...
...و ما همه همسايههاش هستيم. شيرفروش، ستي -
Deliverymen.
يغام رسون
And Dr. Sheehan was there that night?
دكتر شيهان اون شب اونجا بود؟
Yes. He talked about anger.
بله و اون درباره خشم صحبت ميكرد
Tell me about him. What's he like?
دربارش بهم بو اون ه طوريه؟
Uh, he's, uh...
... من فكر ميكنم اون
Okay. Nice.
خوبه، مرد خوبيه
Not hard on the eyes, as my mother would say.
به قول مادرم زياد به شم نمياد
-Did he ever make a pass at you? -No.
هيوقت سراغ شما ميومد؟ - نه -
No, Dr. Sheehan's a good doctor, he would never...
دكتر شيهان دكتر خوبيه ... اون هيوقت
Um...
... آ
(STAMMERING) Could I have a glass of water, please?
ميتونين... ميتونين يه ليوان آب بهم بدين؟
No problem.
مسئلهاي نيست
-Thank you, Marshal. -CHUCK: Sure.
متشكرم مارشال - خواهش ميکنم -
TEDDY: I just have one more question for you, Mrs. Kearns.
فكر ميكنم يه سوال ديه هم از شما دارم خانم كرنز
Did you ever meet a patient named Andrew Laeddis?
شما بيماري به اسم "آندرو ليديس" ميشناسين؟
No.
نه
(VOICE BREAKING) Never heard of him.
هيوقت اسمش رو نشنيدم
TEDDY: She was coached.
داشت نقش بازي ميكرد
She used practically the same words as Cawley and the nurse,
اون همون حرفهايي رو ميزد كه كاولي و رستارها ميفتن
-like she'd been told exactly what to say. -Who's Andrew Laeddis?
انار بهشون فتن كه دقيقا ي بن - آندرو ليديس كيه؟ -
You asked every one of those patients back there about him. Who is he?
تو از همه بيمارها درباره اون رسيدي اون كيه؟
What the hell, boss? I'm your partner, for Christ's sake.
ته رييس؟ من مثلا همكارتم
We just met, Chuck.
ما تازه همديه رو ديديم، اك
You've been on the beat for a long time. You've got a duty. You've got a career.
مدت زيادي با هم نبوديم تو يه کار و وظيقه اي داري که بايد انجام بدي
What I'm doing, it's not exactly by the book.
كه دقيقا براساس قوانين نيست
I don't give a damn about by-the-book, boss.
من هي اهميتي به اون قوانين لعنتي نميدم
I just wanna know what the hell's going on.
فقط ميخوام بدونم اينجا ه خبره
When this case came over the wires,
وقتي اين رونده به واحدمون اومد
I requested it specifically, you understand?
من شخصا خواستم مسئول ييريش بشم، ميفهمي؟
Why?
را؟
Andrew Laeddis,
آندرو ليديس
he was the maintenance man in the apartment building
مسئول نهداري آارتماني بود كه
where my wife and I lived.
من و همسرم توش زندي ميكردم
Okay.
خب؟
He was also a firebug.
اون يه "آتشافروز" هم بوده
Andrew Laeddis lit the match
آندرو ليديس كبريتي رو آتش زده بود
that caused the fire that killed my wife.
.كه باعث آتشسوزي شده بود آتشي كه همسرم رو كشت
GUARD: Let them out!
!بازش كن
CHUCK: What happened to Laeddis? TEDDY: He got away with it.
ه بلايي سر ليديس اومد؟
Laeddis got away with it and then he disappeared.
فرار كرد. ليديس فرار كرد و ناديد شد
About a year ago, I open up the paper and there he is.
يه سال يش يه بار روزنامهاي ميخوندم و اون اونجا بود
Ugly-looking son of a bitch. Huge scar from his right temple down to his left lip.
اون حرومزاده زشت. يه زخمي از شقيقهاش تا بالاي لب سمت ش بود
Eyes different colors. Not the type of face you'd forget.
شمهاي دورنش يزي كه اصلا فراموش نميكنم
He burned down a schoolhouse, killed two people,
اون يه مدرسه رو آتش زده بود و 2 نفر رو كشته بود
said voices told him to do it.
اون فته بود صداهايي توي مغزش بهش فتن اين كارو كنه
First he went to prison, then he got transferred here.
اول به زندان رفت و بعد به اينجا منتقل شد
-Then what? -Then nothing.
بعدش؟ - بعدش هيي -
He vanished like he never existed. No record whatsoever.
اون طوري ناديد شد كه انار اصلا وجود نداشته بدون هي مدركي
Pretty sure he's not in Ward B. That leaves Ward C.
B مطمئنم كه توي ساختون باشه C نيست، بايد توي ساختمون
Or he could be dead.
يا ممكنه مرده باشه
So could Rachel Solando, for that matter.
ممكنه اين اتفاق سر راشل سولاندو هم اومده باشه
Lot of places to hide a body here.
اينجا كلي جا براي مخفي كردن يه جسد هست
Only one place no one would really notice.
ولي فقط يه جا هست كه كسي متوجهش نميشه
That patient, Bridget Kearns, when she sent me for water,
"اون بيمار، "بريجيت كرنز وقتي منو فرستاد دنبال آب
she said something to you back there, didn't she?
يه يزي بهت فت، مه نه؟
No.
نه
Come on, boss.
بيخيال رييس
She wrote it.
اون اينو نوشت
Boss! We gotta get indoors. It's turning into a fucking Kansas out here.
رييس! ما بايد يه سرناه يدا كنيم. طوفان اينجا داره به بدي كانزاس ميشه
-Hold on. -No, let's go!
بسيار خب، برو، برو
Watch out!
!مراقب باش
Jesus!
!خداي من
-Come on! Up there! -Let's go!
!بجنب! بايد بررديم
CHUCK: Get in there! Let's go!
!برو تو! برو
Boss!
!رييس
-God! -Jesus Christ!
!خداي بزر
Damn it. God!
لعنتي !خداي من
-You okay, boss? -Yeah, I'm all right.
حالت خوبه، رييس؟ - آره، خوبم -
So if Laeddis is here,
س فكر ميكني ليديس اينجا باشه
-what are you gonna do about it? -Mmm.
يكار ميخواي بكني، رييس؟
I'm not here to kill Laeddis.
من نيومدم كه ليديس رو بكشم
If it was my wife, I'd kill him. Twice.
اه جاي تو بودم، دوبار ميكشتمش
TEDDY: When we got through the gates at Dachau, the SS guards surrendered.
وقتي ما به دروازههاي "دااو" رسيديم نيروهاي اس.اس تسليم شدن
The Kommandant tried to kill himself before we got there, but he...
فرماندهشون قبل از اينكه ما بهش برسيم سعي كرده بود خودشو بكشه
He botched it.
ولي ند زده بود
Took him an hour to die.
يه ساعت طول كشيد تا بميره
When I went outside, I saw all the bodies on the ground.
وقتي از اونجا رفتم بيرون جنازههايي كه روي زمين بود رو ديدم
Too many to count.
خيلي بيشتر از اوني كه بشه شمردشون
Too many to imagine.
بيشتر از يزي كه تصورش رو كني
So, yeah, the...
خب آره
The guards surrendered, we took their guns,
سربازها تسليم شده بودن، ما اسلحهشون رو رفتيم
and we lined them up.
و به خطشون كرديم
It wasn't warfare. It was...
اين جن عادلانه نبود
It was murder.
جنايت بود
Yeah, I've had enough of killing.
من از كشتن خسته شدم
That's not why I'm here.
س به اين خاطر اينجا نيومدم
-So what is this all about? -(SIGHS)
س قضيه يه؟
After Laeddis vanished, I started doing some checking on Ashecliffe.
بعد از اينكه ليديس ناديد شد من شروع به تحقيق درباره آشكليف كردم
A lot of people know about this place, but no one wants to talk.
مردم زيادي اينجا رو ميشناختن ولي هيكس ... نميخواست حرفي بزنه، ميدوني
You know, it's like it...
...انار
It's like they're scared or something.
انار از يه يزي ميترسيدن
You know, this place is funded by a special grant
ميدونستي بودجه اينجا توسط
from The House Un-American Activities Committee?
كميته فعاليتهاي امريكا" تامين ميشه"
HUAC? And how exactly are we fighting the communists
و ما دقيقا طوري از توي يه جزيره در خليج بوستون
from an island in Boston Harbor?
با دير كشورها ميجنيم؟
By conducting experiments on the mind.
با انجام آزمايش روي ذهن آدمها
At least that's my guess.
حداقل من اينطوري فكر ميكنم
And you think that's going on here?
و تو فكر ميكني اينجا نين كاري ميكنن؟
Like I said, no one would talk, right?
فتم كه هيكس درمورد اينجا حرفي نميزد، خب؟
Till I found somebody who used to be a patient here.
تا يه نفر رو يدا كردم كه قبلا بيمار اينجا بوده
Guy's name is George Noyce. Nice college kid. Socialist.
يه نفر به اسم "جرج نويس" . يه به خوب دانشاهي سوسياليست
He gets offered some money to do a psych study.
بهش يشنهاد ول دادن تا در آزمايشهاي روانشناسي شركت كنه
Guess what they were testing?
حدس بزن ه آزمايشهايي؟
Toothpaste.
آزمايش دارو
So, he starts seeing dragons everywhere.
بعدش شروع كرد به ديدن اژدها در همه جا
He almost beats his professor to death. Ends up here in Ashecliffe, Ward C.
استادش رو تا حد مر كتك زد C و آخرش سر از آشكليف درآورد. ساختمان
They release him after one year, right? And what does he do?
اونها بعد از يه سال آزادش كردن، خب؟ اون يكار كرد
Two weeks on the mainland, he walks into a bar, stabs three men to death.
دو هفته بعدش رفت به يه كافه و سه نفر رو كشت
His lawyer pleads insanity, but Noyce, he stands up in the courtroom and he...
وكيلش ادعا كرد كه اون ديوونه است ... ولي نويس در داداه بلند شد
He begs the judge for the electric chair. Anywhere but a mental hospital.
اون به قاضيها التماس ميكرد كه با صندلي الكتريكي بكشنش هر جا كه بشه، ولي نه در تيمارستان
Judge gives him life in Dedham Prison.
قاضي هم اونو در زندان "ددهام" زنداني كرد
-And you found him. -Yeah, I found him.
و تو اونو يدا كردي - آره، يدا كردم
Well, he's a mess.
اوضاعش خيلي خراب بود
But it's pretty clear from what he tells me.
ولي از حرفهايي كه ميزد، معلوم بود
What?
ي معلوم بود؟
They're experimenting on people here.
اونها آزمايشهايي روي آدمها انجام ميدن
I don't know, boss.
نميدونم رييس
-How do you believe a crazy guy? -That's the beauty of it, isn't it?
من حرفهاي ديوونهها رو باور نميكنم- نكته جالب هم همينه -
Crazy people, they're the perfect subjects. They talk, nobody listens.
آدمهاي ديوونه نكته جالبي دارن اونها حرف ميزنن ولي كسي بهشون وش نميده
I stood at Dachau.
من در "دااو" بودم
We saw what human beings are capable of doing to each other, right?
ما ديديم كه آدمها ه كارهايي ميتونن با همديه بكنن، مه نه؟
For Christ's sakes, we fought a goddamn war to stop them,
محض رضاي خدا، ما يه جن لعنتي كرديم كه جلوي اين كارها رو بيريم
and now... Now I find out it may be happening here? On our soil? No.
حالا فهميديم كه اينجا همين كارها رو ميكنن تو سرزمين خودمون؟ نه
So what are you really here to do, Ted?
س اينجا واقعا دنبال ه كاري هستي، تدي؟
I'm gonna get the proof, I'm gonna go back,
من دنبال مدركم بعدش برميردم
and I'm gonna blow the lid off this place.
و راز اينجا رو افشا ميكنم
That's it.
همين
Wait a minute.
يه لحظه صبر كن
You started asking around about Ashecliffe,
تو دوره افتاده بودي و درباره آشكليف تحقيق ميكردي
waiting for a chance to get out here,
منتظر يه فرصت بودي كه بياي اينجا
and then suddenly they need a U.S. Marshal?
و بعدش يه دفعه اونها به يه مارشال احتياج يدا كردن
Yeah, I got lucky. There was a patient escape. It was the perfect excuse.
من خوششانس بودم كه يه بيمار فرار كرد بهانه خوبي بود
No, no, no, boss. Luck doesn't work that way.
نه، نه، نه رييس شانس اينطوري نيست
The world doesn't work that way.
دنيا اينطوري نيست
They got an electrified fence around a septic facility.
اونها حصارهاي الكتريكي در اطراف اينجا دارن
Ward C is inside a Civil War fort?
C ساختمون در زمان جن داخل يه قلعه نظامي بوده
A Chief of Staff with ties to the OSS? Funding from HUAC?
يه مسئولي كه با اس.اسها در ارتباطه و بودجهاش رو از كميته فعاليت امريكا مييره
I mean, Jesus Christ, everything about this place stinks of government ops.
خداي من! همه يز اينجا بوي ند خرابكاريهاي دولتي ميده
-What if they wanted you here? -Bullshit.
اه اونها ميخواستن تو به اينجا بيايي، ي؟ - مزخرف نو -
-You were asking questions. -Bullshit! Bullshit!
دارم يه سوالي ميرسم - !مزخرف نو -
Bullshit. We came here for Rachel Solando.
مزخرف؟ ما بخاطر راشل سولاندو اينجا اومديم
Where's one shred of evidence she even existed?
اصلا مدركي هست كه نشون بده اون وجود داره؟
There's no way they could've known
اونها ممكن نيست بفهمن
I'd be assigned to this case. There's no way.
كه من به اين رونده ... مربوط بودم، ممكن نيست
What if while you were looking into them, they were looking into you?
وقتي داشتي اطلاعات جمع ميكردي اونها مراقبت بودن
All they had to do was fake an escape to get you here, and now they have you.
تمام كاري كه بايد ميكردن، اين بود كه يه فرار الكي راه بندازن و تو رو بكشن اينجا
Now they have us both. Here! Now!
حالا اونها تو رو دارن، ما رو دارن !اينجا، الان
McPHERSON: (ON MEGAPHONE) Marshals, are you out here?
مارشال، تو اونجايي؟
This is Deputy Warden McPherson.
من افسرنهبان مكفرسون هستم
Marshals!
مارشال
How about that? They found us, huh?
اينو ي ميي؟ اونها يدامون كردن
It's an island, boss. They're always gonna find us.
اينجا يه جزيرست، رييس معلومه كه يدامون ميكنن
I know you're in there.
ميدونم كه اونجايين
We're getting off this goddamn island. You and me. Come on.
ما از اين جزيره خرابشده ميريم تو و من
-Come on! -Go, go!
!بجنب - !بريم -
McPHERSON: Get dried off. Dr. Cawley wants to talk to you now.
لباسهاتون رو خشك كنين !دكتر كاولي ميخواد باهاتون صحبت كنه، حالا
And hurry up! This thing is turning into a goddamn hurricane!
عجله كنين! مطمئنم كه اين قراره !به يه طوفان لعنتي تبديل بشه
I dropped those suits off to be cleaned. Should be ready by tomorrow.
لباسهاتون رو دادم بشورن تا فردا بايد آماده بشن
That is, if we all don't wash away first.
اه طوفان ما رو با خودش نشوره و ببره
You know, speaking of which, I'm afraid your smokes are pretty much done for.
بهرحال، متاسفانه سيارهاتون كاملا خراب شده بود
So...
... س
This is our only choice, huh?
تنها انتخابمون همينه، نه؟
Got something really nice in a prison gray if that don't work for you.
اه ميخواين لباس زندانيها براتون يدا كنم اه اين به دردتون نميخوره
Now that you mention it, these are just fine.
حالا كه فتي، خيلي هم خوبن
That's why I must repeat my insistence that all Ward C patients
بخاطر همين اصرار دارم كه تمام بيماران رو C ساختمان
be placed in manual restraints.
جايي ببريم كه نهبانها خودشون مراقبشون باشن
If the facility floods, they'll drown. You know that.
ار اونجا رو آب بيره، همه اونها غرق ميشن خودتم ميدوني
NAEHRING: That would take a lot of flooding.
طوفان شديدي بايد بياد كه اونجا رو آب بيره
CAWLEY: We're on an island
ما توي يه جزيرهايم
in the middle of the ocean during a hurricane.
وسط اقيانوس در زمان يه طوفان
A lot of flooding seems like a distinct possibility.
طوفان شديد بنظر يز عجيبي نيست
DOCTOR 1: It's a gamble, Stephen. Say the power fails.
اين يه قماره استيون صحبت از اينه كه برقها بره
There's a backup generator.
ما يه ژنراتور ذخيره داريم
And if that goes, the cell doors will open.
و اه اون از کار بيفته؟ - آن موقع در تمام زندانها باز ميشه
Where are they going to go? Mmm?
اونها ميخوان به كجا فرار كنن؟
They can't just hop a ferry, scoot over to the mainland and wreak havoc.
اونها نميتونن سوار كشتي بشن و خودشون رو به سرزمين اصلي برسونن و اونجا رو غارت كنن
NAEHRING: Oh, you're quite right.
درست ميي
They're far more likely to wreak havoc right here on us.
اونها برميردن درست اينجا و ميان سراغ ما
If they're manacled to the floor, they'll die.
اه اونها رو به زمين زنجير كنيم، مي ميرن
This is 24 human beings.
بيست و هار تا انسان
And you can live with that, can you?
نميتوني اينطوري زندي كني، ميتوني؟
Well, frankly, if it were up to me, I'd put all 42 in Wards A and B
روراست بم، اه من بودم
-Excuse me! Excuse me. -CAWLEY: Marshal.
معذرت ميخوام
I'm sorry, Doctor. I just have one quick question.
مارشال - معذرت ميخوام دكتر ولي من يه سوال دارم
Yes, I'll be with you in a moment.
باشه، تا يه دقيقه ديه ميام يشتون
When we spoke this morning about Rachel Solando's note...
ما امروز صبح درباره نوشته راشل سولاندو صحبت كرديم
"The law of four." I love that.
قانون 4 من خوشم اومد
...you said you had no idea what that second line could refer to, correct?
شما فتين كه هي يزي در مورد خط دوم اون به ذهنتون نميرسه
"Who is 67?" Yes, I'm afraid I still don't. None of us do.
شصت و هفتمي كيه؟ بله، متاسفانه هنوزم يزي نميدونم هيكدوم ما نميدونيم
Uh-huh. Nothing comes to mind?
هيي به ذهنتون نميرسه
Nothing?
هيي؟
Because I believe I just heard you say there are 24 patients in Ward C
ون فكر ميكنم شنيدم كه فتين C شما 24 تا بيمار در ساختمون
and 42 patients in Wards A and B,
B دارين و 42 تا در ساختمون
which means there's a total of, what, 66 patients at this facility?
معنيش اينه كه كلا 66 بيمار در اينجا هستن
That is correct, yes.
درسته، بله
Well, it seems to me Rachel Solando was suggesting
بنظر مياد راشل سولاندو نوشته
that you have a 67th patient, Doctor.
كه شما يه بيمار شصت و هفتم در اينجا دارين، دكتر
But I'm afraid we don't.
ولي متاسفانه نداريم
(CHUCKLING) This is ridiculous. What are they doing here?
اين مسخرست - شما اينجا يكار ميكنين؟ -
We're doing our goddamn job.
من دارم كار لعنتيم رو انجام ميدم
Didn't McPherson tell you the good news?
مكفرسون خبرهاي خوب رو به شما نداده؟
(SIGHS) No. What's the good news, Doctor?
نه، خبر خوب يه، دكتر؟
Rachel's been found.
راشل يدا شده
She's here.
اون اينجاست
Safe and sound.
صحيح و سالم
(SOFTLY) There's not a mark on her.
هي علامتي روش نيست
Who are these men?
اين آقايون كي هستن؟
(WHISPERING) Why are they in my house?
را اونها به خونهي من اومدن؟
Police officers, Rachel. They have a few questions.
اونها افسر ليس هستن، راشل اونها... ند تا سوال دارن
Ma'am.
خانم
There has been a sighting of a known communist subversive in this area,
زارشهايي رسيده كه يه كمونيست معروف مشغول توطئه
passing out literature.
و خش اعلاميه در اطراف اينجا هست
Here?
اينجا؟
In this neighborhood?
در همسايي اينجا؟
Yes, I'm afraid so.
بله متاسفانه
Now if you could tell us what you did yesterday, where you were,
حالا اه به ما بين ديروز كجا بودين و يكار ميكردين
it would really help us narrow down our search.
اين خيلي به تحقيقات ما كمك ميكنه
Yes, um...
... بله
Well, I, um...
... خب، من
I made breakfast for Jim and the children,
من براي جيم و بهها صبحانه درست كردم
and then I
... و بعدش من
packed Jim's lunch and he left.
ناهار جيم رو براش ذاشتم و اون رفت
Then I sent the children off to school.
بعدش بهها رو به مدرسه فرستادم
And then
... و بعدش
I decided to take a long swim in the lake.
تصميم رفتم در درياه شنا كنم
I see.
متوجهم
And after that?
و بعدش؟
(SNIFFS) Um...
... آ
After that,
... بعدش
I thought of you.
به فكر تو بودم
(STAMMERING) I'm sorry, ma'am, I don't know what you're talking about.
من... من معذرت ميخوام، خانم نميفهمم ي دارين ميين
Don't you know how lonely I've been, Jim?
نميدوني قدر من تنهايي كشيدم، جيم؟
You're gone.
تو رفتي جيم
You're dead.
تو مردي
I cry every night.
من هر شب ريه ميكردم
How am I supposed to survive?
طور قرار بود زندي كنم؟
God.
خداي من
Rachel, it'll be all right.
راشل... همه يز درست ميشه
I'm so sorry, but every...
... من واقعا متاسفم، ولي
Everything's gonna be all right. Okay?
همه يز درست ميشه، خب؟
I buried you.
من تورو دفن كردم
I buried an empty casket. Your body rained down,
من يه جعبه خالي رو دفن كردم، از بدنت هيي نمونده بود
lumps of flesh splashing into the sea, eaten by sharks.
بغير از خون كوسه تو رو خورد
My Jim's dead, so who the fuck are you?
جيم ِ من مرده س تو ه خري هستي؟
(SCREAMING) Who the fuck are you?
تو ه خري هستي؟
-Who are you? -Hey, hey, hey, hey.
تو كي هستي؟
-It's okay. Rachel. Rachel, it's all right.
تو كي هستي؟ - راشل يزي نيست, يزي نيست -
(SHRIEKING) Let me go! No!
!ولم کنين! نه
-TREY: Rachel, it's okay. -Look at me, look at me.
راشل يزي نيست - !به من ناه کن! به من ناه کن-
I'm sorry about that. I didn't want to interrupt.
من واقعا متاسفم نميخواستم وسط حرفهاتون برم
I thought she might tell you something.
... فكر ميكردم ممكنه حرفي بزنه كه
We found her down by the lighthouse, skipping stones.
ما اونو نزديك فانوس دريايي يدا كرديم از سنها بالا ميرفت
We've no idea how she got out, but...
نميدونيم طوري به اونجا رفته
I'm gonna have to ask you to go down into the basement.
حالا ازتون ميخوام كه باهم به زيرزمين بريم
There's food, water and cots.
اونجا غذا و آب و تختخواب هست
It's the safest place to be when the hurricane hits.
اونجا محل امنتريه ... وقتي كه طوفان شروع بشه
Are you all right? You look pale.
حالتون خوبه؟ رنتون ريده
I'm fine. It's just...
... من خوبم. فقط
CHUCK: Boss, are you okay?
رييس، حالت خوبه؟
It's just so goddamn bright, isn't it?
اينجا... اينجا خيلي روشنه، مه نه؟
Photosensitivity, headaches sometimes. Marshal, are you having a migraine?
حساسيت به نور، بعضي اوقات سردرد مارشال، شما ميرن دارين؟
I'll be all right.
حالم خوب ميشه
Come on, I got you.
اينها رو بيرين مارشال
-(RETCHING) -CHUCK: What's wrong with him?
من م شده؟
Take these, Marshal. Couple of hours, you'll be as clear as a bell.
، ند ساعت خوابتون ميبره بعدش كه بيدار شين حالتون خوب ميشه
-What's wrong with him? -He's having a migraine.
اون شه؟ - اون ميرن داره -
Imagine someone sawed open your head, filled it with razors,
مثل اينه كه يه نفر سرتون رو باز كنه و اونو ر از تيغ كنه
and shook it as hard as they could. Take the pills, Marshal.
و بعد با شدت تمام تكون بده اين قرصها رو بير، مارشال
-I don't... I don't want the pills. -It'll stop the pain.
نه... نه - درد رو كم ميكنه  -
Marshal, take the pills.
قرصها رو بيرين، مارشال
He's going to need to lie down.
اون بايد استراحت کنه
Oh, my God!
اوه، خداي من
NURSE 1: There's broken glass all over the floor.
روي زمين ر از شيشه شکسته است
-Make sure all the meds are locked up. -Watch your back.
در قفسه ها رو قفل کن - مراقب شت سرت باش -
NURSE 2: Make sure everything's okay in Ward B.
B مطمئن شو که در ساختمان همه حالشون خوبه
DOCTOR: Go down to the infirmary and see
به زيرزمين برو و مراقب باش
-if there's any more... -NURSE 3: All right, Doctor.
... اه اونجا - بسيار خب, دکتر -
Give him a bed. This one here.
يه تخت بهم بده
-Over here. All right, boss. -Yeah, that's it.
اينجا، بسيار خب رييس - آره -
-You have him? -TREY: Yes.
حواست هست؟ -
Careful. All right.
مراقب باش
Could be worse right now. He'll be all right.
ممکنه بدتر ميشد الان حالش خوبه
Who is that?
اون كيه؟ - اون؟ -
TREY: Him? That's the warden.
اون زندانبانه
Don't you worry about him, all right? Come on. Lay back. Lay back.
نران اون نباش، خب؟ دراز بکش, دراز بکش
He looks like an ex-military prick, huh?
شبيه يه نظامي عوضيه
Well, you know what? I ain't gonna argue with you on that one.
ميدوني، نميتونم در مورد اون باهات بحث كنم
GIRL: (WHISPERING) You should have saved me.
تو بايد منو نجات بدي
You should have saved all of us.
تو بايد همه ما رو نجات ميدادي
(CHUCKLES) Hey, buddy.
... هي رفيق
Hey.
هي
Laeddis.
ليديس
Yeah.
آره
My...
سلام رفيق
My buddy.
رفيق خودم
No hard feelings, right?
احساس بدي نيست، مه نه؟
Yeah.
آره
No hard feelings.
احساس بدي نيست
A little something for later,
يه يز كوولو باشه براي بعد
'cause I know how much you need it.
ون ميدونم قدر بهش احتياج داري
The clock's ticking, my friend. We're running out of time.
زمان ميذره، دوست من وقتت داره تموم ميشه
Give me a hand here.
كمكم كن
I could get into trouble.
ممكنه به دردسر بيفتم
I'm dead.
من مردم
I'm so sorry.
واقعا متاسفم
Why didn't you save me?
را نجاتم ندادي؟
I tried. I wanted to, but by the time I got there, it was too late.
سعيم رو كردم ولي وقتي رسيدم، خيلي دير شده بود
See?
ميبيني؟
Aren't they beautiful?
قشن نيست؟
Why are you all wet, baby?
را همه لباسهات خيسه، عزيزم؟
Laeddis isn't dead.
ليديس نمرده
He isn't gone.
اون نمرده
He's still here.
اون هنوز اينجاست
I know.
ميدونم
You need to find him, Teddy.
تو بايد يداش كني، تدي
You need to find him and you kill him dead.
تو بايد يداش كني و بكشيش
-(STIFLING SOBS) -It's okay.
بسيار خب
MARINO: Security to Ward A. Okay. ORDERLY 1: Ward A. I got it.
A مراقب بخش باش
NURSE 1: The generator room's flooded.
اتاق ژنراتور رو آب رفته
-ORDERLY 2: Ward A. Ward A. -See what we need in Ward B.
ببين تو بقيه ساختمون ها ي ميخوان؟
NURSE 2: Let's go.
بريم
You okay, boss?
حالت خوبه رييس؟
This goddamn migraine.
!ميرن لعنتي
The backup generator's failed. The whole place has gone crazy.
ژنراتور اصلي از كار افتاده همه يز بهم ريخته
What do you want to do?
ميخواي يكار كني؟
-Christ. -Dan? Relax. Nope, nope, nope.
!خداي من - دن؟ آروم باش, نه, نه -
You don't wanna do that. Put it down. Now. Put it down.
!نه، نه، نه بذارش زمين
Grab him, grab him, grab him, grab him! Get him, get him!
!بيرش! بيرش
ORDERLY 1: You need to go find him 'cause he needs to be here.
بايد يداش کني. بايد بررده
You think the whole electrical system is fried?
فكر ميكني تمام سيستمهاي الكتريكي خراب شدن؟
I'd say it's a good possibility, yeah.
فكر كنم احتمالش زياده
-All the electronic security, the fences... -Why are you always running?
تمام سيستم امنيتي - را هميشه ----------------------؟ -
-...the gates, the doors. -Why is it you every time? Come on.
حصارها، دروازهها و درها - را همش تو؟ -
Nice day for a stroll, don't you think? To Ward C, for example.
روز خوبي براي ردشه اينطور فكر نميكني؟ C مثلا بريم به سمت ساختون
-Come on. -Maybe we'll run into Andrew Laeddis.
شايد آندرو ليديس رو يدا كرديم
TEDDY: The guy I told you about, George Noyce?
آدمي كه دربارش بهت فته بودم جرج نويس
He told me this is where they keep the worst ones.
ميفت اينجا جاييه كه بدترينها رو ميارن
Guys even the other inmates are scared of.
بقيه از اينجا ميترسن
Did Noyce give you anything on the layout?
نويس يزي درباره آزمايشاه بهت نفت؟
Not really. All he remembered was people screaming day and night,
نه واقعا. تنها يزي كه يادش بود صداي جيغ آدمها
no windows and iron bars everywhere.
و اتاقهاي بدون نجره بود و نرده هاي فلزي بود
MAN: Watch your head!
مراقب سرت باش
-Oh, Jesus Christ! -Jesus.
!خداي من
First time on Ward C, huh?
C اولين باريه كه به ساختون مياين، نه؟
-Yeah. -Yeah. Yeah.
آره،آره - ...آره -
We heard stories, but...
... يه يزايي شنيديم اما
Trust me, son, you haven't heard shit.
باور كنيد، بهها. اون يزها دروغ نبوده
We got most of the bugsies locked down now,
بيشترشون رو دوباره زنداني كرديم
but some of them are still loose.
اما ندتاشون هنوز آزادن
And if you see one, don't try to restrain him yourselves.
اه يكيشونو ديدين سعي نكنين جلوشو بيرين
These fuckers will kill you. Clear?
ورنه اونها شما رو ميكشن روشنه؟
All right, get your asses moving then. Go on.
حالا يالا از اينجا برين بجنبين
He's here.
اون اينجاست
Laeddis. I can feel him.
ليديس. احساسش ميكنم
Tag! You're it!
!آفرين! درست فتي
Wait! Boss! Ted!
!صبر کن! رييس! تد
Hey! Hey!
!!!هي!هي
Teddy.
!تدي
Listen to me.
!به من وش كن
Listen, I don't wanna leave here, all right?
وش كن! من نميخوام برم، فهميدي؟
I mean, why would anybody want to?
را کسي بخواد بره؟
We hear things here about the outside world.
من اينجا خيلي يزها شنيدم
-About atolls, about H-bomb tests. -CHUCK: Teddy, where are you?
درباره دنياي بيرون، درباره بمب هيدروژني - تدي، کجايي؟ -
You know how a hydrogen bomb works?
تو ميدوني بمب هيدروژني طور كار ميكنن؟
-I know. With hydrogen! With hydrogen. -Ah, that's funny.
با ...هيدروژن... با هيدروژن - جالب بود -
-Boss! -Other bombs explode, right?
مثل بقيه بمبها منفجر ميشه، درسته؟
But not the hydrogen bomb.
اما هيدروژن از داخل منفجر ميشه
It implodes, creating an explosion to the thousandth, the millionth degree!
انفجاري كه حرارتش ميلياردها درجه است
-Do you get it? -Yeah! Yeah.
فهميدي؟ - آره، آره -
-Do you? -I get it, I get it!
آره، فهميدم، فهميدم -
CHUCK: Let him go!
!بذار بره
CHUCK: No!
!نه
What are you doing?
يكار ميكني؟
Jesus Christ, Teddy. Jesus!
!خداي من! تدي
Oh, you got Billings.
شما " بيلين" رو رفتين
What the fuck's the matter with you guys?
شماها تون شده؟
Catch them, not kill them!
بايد اونها رو بيرين !نه اينكه بكشين
-He jumped us. -GUARD: You, give me a hand with him.
اون به ما حمله كرد - ! کمکم کن -
We've gotta get him to the infirmary. God damn it.
كمكم كن بايد به درماناه ببرمش، لعنتي
No, no! Not you, not you. Take a walk.
!نه، نه! تو نه برو يه قدمي بزن
Come on. Cawley's gonna have my goddamn balls for this.
!بجنب کاولي درم رو در مياره
MAN: (WHISPERING) Laeddis.
ليديس
INMATE: (SOFTLY) Stop me, please,
خواهش ميکنم جلومو بير
(SOBBING) before I kill more.
قبل از اينکه کس ديه رو بکشم
MAN: (WHISPERING) Laeddis.
ليديس
INMATE: Please, please.
!خواهش ميكنم! خواهش ميكنم
MAN: (WHISPERING) I see you all.
همش تو رو ميبينم
Laeddis.
... ليديس
You told me I'd be free of this place.
تو فتي منو از اينجا آزاد ميكني
You promised.
تو قول دادي
You lied.
تو دروغ فتي
Laeddis.
ليديس
Laeddis?
ليديس؟
(CHUCKLES) That's pretty damn funny.
خيلي خندهداره
-Your voice. -Don't you recognize it?
... صدات نشناختيش؟
After all the talks we had?
بعد از اون همه صحبتهايي كه داشتيم
After all the lies you told me?
بعد از آن همه دروغهايي كه بهم فتي
Let me see your face.
بذار صورتت رو ببينم
They say I'm theirs now.
اونها مين من الان مال اونها هستم
They say I'll never leave here.
اونها مين من هيوقت اينجا رو ترك نميكنم
Your match is about to go out.
كبريتت داره تموم ميشه
-Let me see your goddamn face! Now! -Why?
!بذار صورت لعنتيت رو ببينم - براي ي؟ -
So you can lie to me more?
ميخواي دوباره بهم دروغ بي؟
-This isn't about the truth. -Yes, it is.
اين درباره حقيقت نيست - را هست -
-It's about exposing the truth. -It's about you!
اين درباره افشا كردنه - !اين درباره توئه -
And Laeddis.
و درباره ليديس
That's all it's ever been about.
يزي كه هميشه درباره اون بوده
I was incidental. A way in.
من مجبور بودم يه راه ورود
George... George Noyce.
جرج؟ جرج نويس؟
No. It's not possible. You can't be here.
نه، ممكن نيست تو اينجا باشي
You like it?
خوشت مياد؟
Who did this to you, George?
كي اين كارو باهات كرده، جرج؟
You did.
تو كردي
What the hell do you mean?
منظورت يه؟
All your talk. All your fucking talk, and I'm back in here because of you.
تمام حرفهاي مزخرفت و من بخاطر تو برشتم اينجا
George, how did they get you out of Dedham, huh?
جرج، طور تو رو از زندان ددهام در آوردن؟ هان؟
(STAMMERING) However this happened, I...
هر اتفاقي که افتاده باشه
I'm gonna find a way to fix this, you understand me?
من درستش ميکنم ميفهمي؟
I'll never get out now. I got out once. Not twice, never twice.
حالا هيوقت من از اينجا بيرون نميايم !من يه بار از اينجا بيرون رفتم. ولي ديه نميرم، ديه نميرم
Just tell me how they got you here.
بهم بو طوره آوردنت اينجا؟
They knew! Don't you get it?
اونها ميدونستن نفهميدي؟
Everything you were up to. Your whole plan.
هر يزي كه بهت مربوط بود تمام نقشهات
This is a game. All of this is for you.
اين يه بازيه همش براي تو
You're not investigating anything. You're a fucking rat in a maze.
تو مشغول هي تحقيقي نبودي تو يه موش لعنتي توي يه مازي
Georgie...
... جرج
-George, you're wrong. You're wrong. -Oh, really?
جرج، اشتباه ميكني - واقعا؟ -
Been alone much since you got here?
از وقتي اينجا اومدي خيلي تنها شدي؟
I've been with my partner.
من با همكارم هستم
You never worked with him before, have you?
همكاري كه هيوقت قبلا باهاش كار نكرده بودي؟
He's a U.S. Marshal. He's...
... اون يه مارشال امريكاييه
(INSISTENTLY) You never worked with him before, have you?
تو هيوقت قبلا باهاش كار نكرده بودي، كرده بودي؟
George, look, I know people. I trust this man.
... جرج، ببين من آدمها رو ميشناسم، به اون اعتماد دارم
Then they've already won.
س، اونها از همين الان برنده شدن
(WHIMPERS) Fuck.
!لعنتي
And they're gonna take me to the lighthouse.
اونها ميان و منو به فانوس دريايي ميبرن
They're gonna cut into my brain.
اونها ميخوان مغزم رو سوراخ كنن
And I'm only here
من بخاطر تو اينجا هستم
(SHOUTING) because of you!
!بخاطر تو
George, I'm gonna get you out of here.
جرج، من از اينجا درت ميارم
You're not going to the lighthouse. You're not.
تو رو به فانوس دريايي نميبرن
You can't dig out the truth and kill Laeddis at the same time.
تو نميتوني هم ليديس رو بكشي و هم حقيقت رو بفهمي
You gotta make a choice. You understand that, don't you?
تو بايد انتخاب كني، ميفهمي، مه نه؟
-I'm not here to kill anyone. -Liar!
من نيومدم اينجا كه كسي رو بكشم - !دروغو -
I'm not gonna kill him, I swear to you! I swear.
من كسي رو نمي كشم، قسم ميخورم -
She's dead.
اون مرده
She... Let her go.
بذار بره
DOLORES: Tell him, Teddy. Tell him why.
بو تدي... بهش بو را
GEORGE: You gotta do it. There's no other way.
بايد اين كارو كني اره ديهاي نداري
-Let her go. -Tell him about the day
بذار بره - بهش درباره روزي بو كه -
-you brought me my locket. -You gotta do it!
وقي تو ل برام آوردي - !تو بايد اين كارو كني -
How I told you my heart was breaking and you asked me why.
و من فتم قلبم شكسته و تو رسيدي را؟
She's fucking with your head.
اون داره با ذهنت بازي ميكنه
And I told you it was from happiness.
بهت كه فتم از خوشحاليمه
She's gonna kill you.
اون تو رو ميكشه !اون تو رو ميكشه
You wanna uncover the truth? You gotta let her go.
ميخواي واقعيت رو بفهمي؟ بايد بذاري بره
-I can't. -You have to let her go!
نميتونم - !تو بايد بذاري بره -
I can't! I can't.
!نميتونم
Then you'll never leave this island.
س هيوقت اين جزيره رو ترك نميكني
Dolores.
دلورس؟
He's not in this ward.
اون اينجا نيست
He was transferred out of here.
اونو منتقل كردن بيرون اينجا
If he's not in Ward A, there's only one place he can be.
A توي ساختمان هم نيست. فقط ميتونه يه جا باشه
The lighthouse.
فانوس دريايي
Hey,
!هي
God help you.
خدا كمكت كنه
CHUCK: Boss, we got problems.
يه مشكلي داريم
McPherson and Cawley are in the building.
كاولي و مكفرسون داخل ساختمونن
They heard an orderly went batshit on a patient.
كاولي شنيده كه يكي از مستخدمها با يه بيمار درير شده
They're looking all over the place for him and they're on their way to the roof.
حالا داره همه جا رو دنبالش ميرده
Let's get the hell out of here. This way.
بايد از اينجا بريم بيرون از اين طرف
Just keep going. We belong here.
به راهت ادامه بده ما هم جز اونهاييم
What happened to you?
ه اتفاقي برات افتاد؟
-What do you mean? -I mean,
منظورت يه؟ - كجا بودي؟ -
where were you?
بعد از اينكه اون بيمار رو به درماناه برديم بعدش رفتم به روندههاي بيمارها سرك كشيدم
After we got that guy to the infirmary, I took a little detour to patient records.
ليديس رو يدا كردي؟
Did you ever find Laeddis?
نه
No. No, I never found him.
نه يداش نكردم
Well, I got the next best thing. His intake form.
خب من يزهاي خوبي يدا كردم فرم ذيرش اون بيمار
It was the only thing in his files. There's no session notes,
تنها يزي بود كه در روندهاش بود نه صورت جلسهاي، نه زارشي
no incident reports, no photographs, just this. It was weird.
نه عكسي، فقط همين، عجيبه
Here. Take a look.
بيا يه ناهي بنداز
I'll look at it later.
بعدا
What's the matter, boss?
رييس ي شده؟
I'll look it over later, that's all.
بعدا ميبينمش فقط همين
-Ashecliffe's that way. -I'm not going to Ashecliffe.
آشكليف از اونطرفه - به آشكليف برنميردم -
I'm going to that lighthouse.
ميرم به فانوس دريايي اونجا
I'm gonna find out what the fuck is happening on this island.
ميخوام بفهمم توي اين جزيره خرابشده ي ميذره
TEDDY: There it is.
اونجاست
Damn. We're too far south. We're gonna have to double back.
لعنتي! خيلي به سمت شمال رفتيم بايد تمام مسير رو بررديم
There's no way we could cross those rocks.
هي راهي نيست كه از اون صخرهها بذريم
There could be a way behind those trees.
بايد يه راهي شت اون درختها باشه
Maybe a path that goes around the rocks and leads over to the lighthouse.
شايد يه راه به سمت فانوس دريايي باشه كه بتونيم اون صخرهها رو دور بزنيم
-Boss... -Come on.
... رييس - عجله كن -
Wait, wait, what are we doing? We got the intake form.
ما اينجا يكار ميكنيم؟ ما فرم ذيرشي داريم
It's proof there's a 67th patient,
كه ثابت ميكنه بيمار 67 ام اينجا هست
which they said, repeatedly, doesn't exist.
كه اونها وجودش رو انكار ميكنن
I'm getting to that lighthouse. You understand?
من ميرم به اون فانوس دريايي فهميدي؟
What the hell can I say to you to stop you?
طوري بايد جلوي تو رو بيرم
Why would you want to, Chuck? Why?
را ميخواي جلوي منو بيري؟ را؟
Because climbing down there when it's dark
ون ايين رفتن از اون صخرهها توي تاريكي، مثل خودكشيه
is a thin step short of suicide, that's why.
بهيمن خاطر جلوي تورو مييرم
Okay, maybe you better sit this one out then.
بسيار خب. شايد بهتر باشه همينجا بموني
You brought me into this, boss,
تو منو به اينجا آوردي
and now we're trapped here on this rock, on this island,
حالا من اينجا روي اين صخره ير افتادم در اين جزيره
with no one to rely on but each other,
به هيكس هم نميشه اعتماد كرد
-and now you're acting like... -Like what? Like what?
... و حالا طوري رفتار ميكني انار - مثل ي؟ -
How am I acting?
طور رفتار ميكنم؟
What the hell happened back there in those cells, Ted?
توي اون زندان ه اتفاقي افتاد، تد؟
What do you think the weather's like in Portland, Chuck?
فكر ميكني هوا در رتلند طوره، اك؟
I'm from Seattle.
من اهل سياتل هستم
Seattle.
سياتل؟
I'm going on
...من ميرم
alone.
تنها
-I'm going with you, boss. -I said alone.
باهات ميام همكار - فتم، تنها -
Fine.
بسيار خب
Damn it!
!لعنتي
I knew it wouldn't take long, but I couldn't get to it.
ميدونستم خيلي طول ميكشه ... ولي فكر نميكردم
The tide was up.
مد دريا شروع بشه
Chuck!
!اك
Come on!
يالا
Where are you, Chuck?
كجايي؟
Chuck!
!اك
Who are you?
تو كي هستي؟
I'm Teddy Daniels. I'm a cop.
من تدي دانيلز هستم يه ليسم
You're the marshal.
تو مارشال هستي
That's right.
درسته
Would you mind taking your hand from behind your back, please?
ميشه ... دستت رو از شتت در بياري؟
Why? Why?
را؟ را؟
I wanna make sure that what you're holding won't hurt me.
ميخوام مطمئن بشم يزي كه مخفي كردي، به من صدمه نميزنه
I'm gonna keep this
اينو نه ميدارم
if you don't mind.
اه اشكالي نداشته باشه
Fine by me.
عيبي نداره
You're...
... تو
You're Rachel Solando.
راشل سولاندو هستي
The real one.
راشل سولاندوي واقعي
Did you kill your children?
و تو بههات رو كشتي؟
I never had children.
من هيوقت بهاي نداشتم
I was never married.
من هيوقت ازدواج نكردم
And before I was a patient at Ashecliffe, I worked here.
قبل از اينكه بيمار اينجا باشم، اينجا كار ميكردم
You... You were a nurse?
تو يه رستار بودي؟
I was a doctor, Marshal.
من يه دكتر بودم، مارشال
You think I'm crazy.
تو فكر ميكني من ديوانهام؟
-No. No, no, I never... -And if I say I'm not crazy?
... نه، من - و اه بم من ديوونه نيستم -
Well, that hardly helps, does it?
كمكي نميكنه، ميكنه؟
That's the Kafkaesque genius of it.
اين نبوغ "كافكاييه" اينه
People tell the world you're crazy,
مردم بهت مين ديوونه
and all your protests to the contrary just confirm what they're saying.
و سعي نكن باهاشون مخالفت كني فقط يزي كه مين رو تاييد كن
I'm not following you. I'm sorry.
من تعقيبت نميكردم متاسفم
Once you're declared insane,
وقتي بهت برسب ديووني زدن
then anything you do is called part of that insanity.
بعدش هر كاري كه بكني ديووني محسوب ميشه
Reasonable protests are denial. Valid fears, paranoia.
انكار يا مقاومت ترس واقعي، توهم
Survival instincts are
غريزه زنده موندن
defense mechanisms.
بعنوان يه سيستم دفاعي
You're smarter than you look, Marshal. That's probably not a good thing.
باهوشتر از يزي كه بنظر مياي، هستي مارشال و اين مسلما يز خوبي نيست
-Tell me something. -Yeah.
... يه يزي رو بهم بو
What happened to you?
ه اتفاقي برات افتاده؟
I started asking about these large shipments of sodium amytal
من در مورد حمل اين همه سديم و داروهاي روانزشكي سديمدار
and opium-based hallucinogens.
به اين جزيره سوال كردم
Psychotropic drugs.
داروهاي رواندرماني
I asked about the surgeries, too.
شروع كردم به سوال كردن در مورد عملهاي جراحي
You ever heard of a transorbital lobotomy?
تا حالا اسم عمل خارج كردن قسمتي از مغز رو شنيدي؟
They zap the patient with electroshock,
روي سر بيمار دستاه شوك الكتريكي ميذارن
then go through the eye with an ice pick,
بعد با يخشكن و از طريق شم
pull out some nerve fibers.
تعدادي از عصبها رو خارج ميكنن
Makes the patients much more obedient.
اينطوري بيمارها رو مطيع خودشون ميكنن
Tractable.
سربراهشون ميكنن
It's barbaric,
اين وحشيانه است
unconscionable.
بي وجدانيه
Do you know how pain enters the body, Marshal? Do you?
ميدوني درد طوري وارد بدن ميشه، مارشال؟ ميدوني؟
Depends on where you're hurt?
بستي به جايي كه درد ميكنه، داره
No, it has nothing to do with the flesh.
نه، اين هي ربطي به جسم نداره
The brain controls pain.
اين مغزه كه درد رو كنترل ميكنه
The brain controls fear, empathy, sleep, hunger, anger. Everything.
مغزه كه ترس، دلسوزي، خواب، خشم و رسني و همه يز رو كنترل ميكنه
What if you could control it?
حالا اه بتوني اون رو كنترل كني، ي ميشه؟
-You mean the brain? -Recreate a man
مغز رو كنترل كني؟ - ساختن انساني -
so he doesn't feel pain or love or sympathy.
كه درد رو حس نميكنه يا عشق يا دلسوزي
A man who can't be interrogated,
مردي كه نميشه ازش اعتراف رفت
because he has no memories to confess.
ون حافظهاي نداره كه بخواد به يزي اعتراف كنه
You can never take away all a man's memories. Never.
اونها نميتونن تمام خاطرات !يه نفر رو ازش بيرن. هرز
Marshal, the North Koreans used American POWs
كره شماليها روي زندانيهاي جني امريكا
during their brainwashing experiments.
طي آزمايش شستشوي مغزي اين كارها را ميكردن
They turned soldiers into traitors. That's what they're doing here.
اونها سربازها رو به خيانتكارهايي تبديل كردن اين كاريه كه اينجا دارن انجام ميدن
They're creating ghosts to go out in the world
اونها ارواحي ساختن كه در دنيا كارهايي بكنن
and do things sane men... Sane men never would.
كه هي انساني انجامش نميده
To have that kind of ability, that kind of knowledge,
رسيدن به نين دانش و توانايي
-that would take years. -Years. Years of research.
سالها كار ميبره - سالها تحقيق -
Hundreds of patients to experiment on.
آزمايش روي صدها بيمار
Fifty years from now, people will look back and say, here, this place,
نجاه سال بعد از اين مردم برميردن و يه اينجا ناه  ... ميكنن و مين
is where it all began.
همه يز از اينجا شروع شد
The Nazis used the Jews, Soviets used prisoners in their own Gulags, and we,
نازيها از يهوديها استفاده ميكردن ... شوروي از زندانيهاش در ولا. و ما
we tested patients on Shutter Island.
ما ما روي بيمارها آزمايش ميكرديم در جزيره شاتر
No, they won't.
نه؛ اونها نين كاري نميكنن
No.
نه
You do understand
تو فهميدي كه
that they can't let you leave.
نميتونن بهت اجازه بدن از اينجا بري
I am a federal marshal. They can't stop me.
من يه مارشال فدرال هستم اونها نميتونن جلوي منو بيرن
I was an esteemed psychiatrist from a respected family.
منم روانزشك مشهوري بودم از يه خانوادهي  محترم
Didn't matter.
ولي مهم نبود
Let me ask you. Any past traumas in your life?
بذار يه سوالي ازت برسم قبلا در زنديت هي آسيب روحي نديده بودي؟
Yes.
آره
But why would that matter?
را، ه اهميتي داره؟
Because they're gonna point to some event in your past
ون اونها مين اتفاقاتي كه در ذشته افتاده
and say it's the reason you lost your sanity.
باعث شده كه عقلش رو از دست بده
So that when they commit you here, your friends and colleagues will say,
س وقتي تو رو به اينجا فرستادن دوستات و همكارات مين
"Of course he cracked.
اون ديوونه شده بوده
"Who wouldn't after what he'd been through?"
كي فكر ميكرد اين بلا سرش بياد؟
They can say that about anyone, anyone at all.
براي هر كسي ممكنه اين اتفاقات افتاده باشه
The point is they're gonna say it about you.
براي هر كسي - موضوع اينه كه اين درباره توئه -
-How's your head? -My head?
توي سرت ي ميذره؟ - توي سرم؟ -
Any funny dreams lately? Trouble sleeping?
روياهاي مسخره؟ ... مشكلات خواب
-Headaches? -I am prone to migraines, yes.
سردرد - من ميرن دارم -
Jesus.
!خداي من
You haven't taken any pills, have you? I mean, even aspirin?
تو هي قرصي از اونها نرفتي، رفتي؟ حتي يه مُسكن؟
-The aspirin? -Jesus.
مُسكن؟ - خداي من -
And you ate the food in the cafeteria and drank the coffee they gave you?
و تو اون غذا و قهوه اونجا رو خوردي؟
You tell me, at least, that you've been smoking your own cigarettes.
حداقل بو كه فقط سيارهاي خودتو ميكشيدي
No.
نه... نه
No, I haven't.
نه نكشيدم
It takes 36 to 48 hours for neuroleptic narcotics
بين 36 تا 48 ساعت طول ميكشه كه
to reach workable levels in the bloodstream.
اون دارو اثرش رو بذاره
Palsy comes first,
اول لرزش بدن شروع ميشه
first the fingertips, then eventually the whole hand.
اول انشتات و بعد تمام دستت
Seen any walking nightmares lately, Marshal? Huh?
اخيرا كابوس نميبيني مارشال؟
Tell me what goes on in that lighthouse.
بهم بو توي اون فانوس دريايي ي ميذره؟
Tell me.
بهم بو
Brain surgery.
عمل مغز
The let's-open-the-skull-and-see- what-happens-if-we-pull-on-this kind.
مثل بازكردن جمجمه و برداشتن قسمتي از مغز تا ببينن بعدش ه اتفاقي ميفته
The learned-it-from-the-Nazis kind.
مثل كاري كه نازيها ميكردن
That's where they create the ghosts.
و بعدش اون ارواح رو ميسازن
Who knows about this? On the island, I mean. Who?
كي از اين موضوع خبر داره؟ منظورم داخل جزيره است. كي؟
Everyone.
همه
Come on. The nurses? The orderlies?
بي خيال، حتي رستارها و خدمتكارها؟
-They couldn't possibly know... -(FIRMLY) Everyone.
... اين ممكن نيست - همه ميدونن -
You can't stay here.
تو نميتوني اينجا بموني
They think I'm dead, that I drowned.
اونها فكر ميكنن، من مردم، غرق شدم
I'm afraid if they come looking for you, they might find me.
اه به دنبال تو بيان، ممكنه منو يدا كنن
I'm sorry, but you have to go.
متاسفم ولي تو بايد بري
I'm gonna come back for you.
برميردم دنبالت
I won't be here. I move during the day. New places every night.
آن موقع من اينجا نيستم. من هر روز جايم رو عوض ميكنم و شب يه جاي تازه ميمونم
But I could come get you, get you off this island.
اما من ميتونم تو رو از اين جزيره ببرم
Haven't you heard a word I've said?
حرفهايي كه بهت زدم رو نشنيدي؟
The only way off the island is the ferry, and they control it.
تنها راه خروج از اينجا كشتيه كه اونها كنترلش ميكنن
You'll never leave here.
تو هيوقت اينجا رو ترك نميكني
I had a friend.
من يه دوست داشتم
I was with him yesterday, but we got separated.
اون ديروز همراه من بود و بعد از هم جدا شديم
Have you seen him?
اونو نديدي؟
Marshal,
... مارشال
you have no friends.
تو دوستي نداري
There you are.
اينجايي
We were wondering when you'd show up.
ميخواستيم بدونيم كي يدات ميشه
Have a seat.
بيا بشين
Come on.
!بجنب
Taking a leisurely stroll, were we?
داشتي با خيال راحت براي خودت قدم ميزدي؟
I was just looking around.
فقط... فقط داشتم اطراف رو ميشتم
Did you enjoy God's latest gift?
از آخرين هديه خداوند خوشت اومد؟
-What? -God's gift.
ي؟ - هديه خداوند -
The violence.
خشونت
When I came downstairs in my home and I saw that tree in my living room,
وقتي از لهها در خونهام اومدم ايين و يه درخت رو در اتاق نشيمن ديدم، بنظرم مثل
it reached out for me like a divine hand.
مثل يه دست مقدس به سوي من دراز شده بود
God loves violence.
خداوند عاشق خشونته
-I hadn't noticed. -(CHUCKLES) Sure you have.
تا حالا متوجه نشده بودم - مطمئنم كه شده بودي
Why else would there be so much of it?
زياد بودنش ه دليل ديهاي ميتونه داشته باشه؟
It's in us.
در وجود ماست
It's what we are.
يزي كه هستيم
We wage war, we burn sacrifices,
ما جن راه ميندازيم، قربانيها رو ميسوزونيم
and pillage and plunder and tear at the flesh of our brothers.
قتل و غارت ميكنيم وشت برادرهامون رو هم ميخوريم
And why? Because God gave us violence to wage in his honor.
و را؟ ون خدا به ما خشونت داده كه به اسم اون جن راه بندازيم
I thought God gave us moral order.
فكر ميكنم خداوند بهمون اخلاقيات هم داده
There's no moral order as pure as this storm.
هي اخلاقياتي به خالصي اين طوفان وجود نداره
There's no moral order at all. There's just this,
اصلا اخلاقياتي وجود نداره
can my violence conquer yours?
فقط يه يزي هست خشونت من ميتونه تو رو شكست بده يا نه؟
-I'm not violent. -Yes, you are.
من خشن نيستم - را هستي -
You're as violent as they come.
تو به اندازهي اونها خشن هستي
I know this because I'm as violent as they come.
من ميدونم، ون من هم به اندازهي اونها خشن هستم
If the constraints of society were lifted,
ار فشار جامعه از ما برداشته ميشد
and I was all that stood between you and a meal,
و من بين غذايم و تو ايستاده باشم
you would crack my skull with a rock and eat my meaty parts.
تو با سن سرمو ميشكستي و غذايم رو برميداشتي
Wouldn't you?
مه نه؟
Cawley thinks you're harmless, that you can be controlled,
كاولي فكر ميكنه تو بي خطري، و قابل كنترلي
but I know different.
ولي من اينطور فكر نميكنم
-You don't know me. -Oh, but I do.
تو منو نميشناسي - اوه، من تو رو ميشناسم-
-No, you don't. You don't know me at all. -Oh, I know you.
نه، تو اصلا منو نميشناسي - را ميشناسم -
We've known each other for centuries.
ما قرنهاست همديه رو ميشناسيم
If I was to sink my teeth into your eye right now,
اه الان دندونهامو ميكردم توي شمت
would you be able to stop me before I blinded you?
ميتوني قبل از اينكه كورت كنم، جلوي منو بيري؟
Give it a try.
سعيم رو ميكنم
That's the spirit.
اين سرشت توئه
Don't worry, because we're going to get you back to your room.
نران نباش، تو رو به اتاقت برميردونيم
-Not really. -Something I've seen.
در واقع نه - من يزهايي ديدم -
Okay.
بسيار خب
Where have you been?
كجا بودي؟
Oh, just wandering. Just looking at your island.
رخ ميزدم. داشتم جزيرهات رو ميديدم
Oh, I forgot you're leaving now that Rachel's been found.
حالا كه راشل يدا شده، تو از اينجا ميري
-GLEN: Stop looking at him. -For sure. Yeah.
بهش ناه نكن - باشه، حتما -
Stop looking at him. Stop looking at him.
بهش ناه نكن
-Big meeting? -Oh, yes.
جلسه بزريه - اوه، آره -
-It's okay. I'm... -I don't like that.
مهم نيست - من خوشم نمياد -
Apparently there was an unidentified man
C ظاهرا ديروز يه مرد ناشناس به ساختون
in Ward C yesterday.
رفته بوده
He subdued a highly dangerous patient quite handily.
و خيلي خوب يكي از بيمارهاي خطرناكمون رو ادب كرده
Is that so?
واقعا؟
It seems he had a long conversation with a paranoid schizophrenic,
و ظاهرا فتوي طولاني با بيمار دوشخصيتي
George Noyce.
به اسم "جورج نويس" داشته
BRIDGET: Well, I don't remember what I'm supposed to remember.
خب، يادم نمياد ي رو بايد بخاطر بيارم
We're gated down. We're fine.
ما دروازه رو بستيم همه حالشون خوبه
This Noyce, you said his name was, he's delusional?
اين "نويس"؛ فتي اسمش اينه اون توهم داره؟
Oh, extremely. He can be quite upsetting.
به شدت،اون دار افسرديه
As a matter of fact, two weeks ago,
در واقع دو هفته يش، يه بيمار اونقدر
a patient got so wound up by one of Noyce's stories that he beat him up.
سر يكي از داستانهاش سربسرش ذاشت كه "نويس" حسابش رو رسيد
-Hmm. -Cigarette?
سيار ميكشي؟
No, thanks. I quit.
نه ممنون. ترك كردم
-So you're taking the ferry? -Yes, absolutely.
س با كشتي ميري؟ - بله، البته -
I think we've gotten all we came here for, so...
فكر ميكنم به تمام كارهايي كه ما بخاطرش به اينجا اومديم، رسيديم
"We," Marshal?
ما"، مارشال؟"
Speaking of which, have you seen him, Doctor?
درباره همكارم صحبت ميكنم
Who?
تو اونو ديدي، دكتر؟ - كي رو؟ -
My partner, Chuck.
همكارم، اك
You don't have a partner, Marshal. You came here alone.
تو همكاري نداري، مارشال تو تنها اينجا اومدي
You know, I've built something valuable here,
ميدوني، من اينجا يه يز رانبها ساختم
and valuable things have a way of being misunderstood in their own time.
اما يزهاي رانبها هميشه در زمان خودشون با بدفهمي مواجه ميشن
Everyone wants a quick fix. They always have.
همه ميخوان سريع به هدفشون برسن هميشه همينطور بوده
I'm trying to do something that people, yourself included, don't understand.
من سعي دارم كاري بكنم كه مردم، و حتي تو متوجه نميشين
And I'm not going to give up without a fight.
و من بدون مبارزه تسليم نميشم
I can see that.
متوجهم
Mmm.
ممم
So, tell me again about your partner.
س دوباره درباره همكارت بهم بو
What partner?
كدوم همكار؟
It's fine.
خوبه
ORDERLY: She made a mess. I cleaned it up. She made a mess again.
اون دوباره كثافت كاري كرد من تميزش ميكنم
Marshal,
... مارشال
going somewhere?
جايي ميرفتي؟
(STAMMERING) I'm just heading out to the ferry, so...
نه، فقط... فقط ميرفتم كه به كشتي برسم
Ah! Oh, well, I'm afraid it's the other way.
معذرت ميخوام. ولي اون از اونطرفه
Oh?
واقعا؟
If you'll wait a moment, I'll find you someone who can take you to the dock.
اه يه لحظه صبر كني يه نفر رو يدا ميكنم كه به اونجا ببردت
-What's this, Doctor? Huh? What's this? -It's just a sedative.
اين يه، دكتر؟ هان؟ اين يه؟ - اين فقط يه آمول مسكنه -
-A precaution. -Oh! A precaution.
محض احتياط - محض احتياط؟ -
What are you going to do? Kill me?
ميخواي يكار كني؟ منو بكشي؟
-Marshal. -You think you deserve it?
مارشال - فكر ميكني حقت نيست -
For what, hmm? Provoking you?
براي ي؟ براي اينكه عصبانيت كردم؟
Well, forgive me. What doesn't provoke you?
و معذرت ميخوام ي تو رو عصباني نميكنه؟
-Remarks? Words? -Nazis?
... توجه كردن...  حرف زدن- نازيها -
Well, that, too. And, of course, memories, dreams.
خب اونم هست ... و البته، خاطرات، روياها
Did you know that the word "trauma" comes from the Greek for "wound"?
ميدونستي كلمه تروما (آسيب روحي) از كلمه يوناني "زخم" رفته شده؟
And what is the German word for "dream"?
"و " رويا" به آلماني ميشه " ترومن
Traum. Ein Traum.
رويا ميبينم
Wounds can create monsters, and you...
زخمها ميتونن هيولاها بسازن
You are wounded, Marshal.
و تو زخمي شدي، مارشال
And wouldn't you agree, when you see a monster,
فكر ميكنم باهام موافق باشي كه وقتي يه هيولا ديدي
you must stop it?
بايد متوقفش كني
Yeah.
آره
-I agree. -Yes.
موافقم - البته -
Yeah.
آره
ORDERLY 1: I told him that we'd take about an hour to do it.
بهش فتم كه يه ساعت طول ميكشه تا انجامش بديم
ORDERLY 2: Yeah. Did they say we're going to do the first floor?
آره، بهش فتي ميريم سراغ طبقه اول؟
ORDERLY 1: How long you been the clock?
ند ساعته اينجايي؟
ORDERLY 2: I've been on for 18 hours straight.
الان 18 ساعته كه سرام
ORDERLY 1: Nice paycheck.
دستمزدش خوبه
DOLORES: What are you doing, baby?
يكار ميكني، عزيزم؟
-You gotta get to the ferry. -No.
بايد به اسكله برسي
No, no.
نه... نه... نه
Yeah.
آره
If the world thinks that Chuck is dead, then he's perfect for their experiments.
اه اونها مين كه اك مرده، س اون براي اينكه روش آزمايش بشه مناسبه
There's only one place they'd take him.
فقط يه جايي هست كه اونو ببرن
-You go there and you'll die. -He's my partner.
اه به اونجا بري، ميميري - اون همكارمه -
If they are hurting him, if they're holding him against his will,
اه اونها بهش صدمه بزنن و اه برخلاف ميلش زندانياش كنن
I've gotta bring him out.
من بايد برش ردونم
I can't lose anyone else.
نميتونم كس ديهاي رو از دست بدم
Don't go, Teddy, please.
به اونجا نرو، خواهش ميكنم به اونجا نرو
-Please, don't do this. Don't go. -I'm sorry, honey.
خواهش ميكنم، نرو - معذرت ميخوام، عزيزم -
I'm sorry, honey.
معذرت ميخوام عزيزم
I love this thing because you gave it to me,
من اين كراوات رو خيلي دوست دارم ون تو اونو بهم دادي
but the truth is
... اما در حقيقت
it is one fucking ugly tie.
اين يه كراوات زشت لعنتيه
No.
!نه
Don't move. Stay where you are.
!حركت نكن! همونجايي كه هستي بمون
Are you gonna kill me?
ميخواي منو بكشي؟
No, I'm not gonna kill you.
نه، تو رو نميكشم
Why are you all wet, baby?
را خيس شدي، عزيزم؟
-What did you say? -You know exactly what I said.
ي فتي؟ - دقيقا ميدوني ي فتم -
The rifle's empty, by the way.
بهرحال اون اسلحه خاليه
Have a seat.
بشين
For God's sake, dry off. You'll catch cold.
محض رضاي خدا، خودت رو خشك كن سرما ميخوري
All right.
بسيار خب
How badly did you hurt the guard?
قدر به اون نهبان صدمه زدي؟
(STAMMERING) I don't know what you're talking about.
نميفهمم ي داري ميي؟
Yes, he's here.
بله، اون اينجاست
Have Dr. Sheehan take a look at your man before you send him up.
قبل از اينكه بفرستيدش بالا، دكتر شيهان خوب معاينهاش كرد؟
So Dr. Sheehan came in on the ferry this morning, huh?
... س، دكتر شيهان امروز با كشتي برشته؟
Not exactly.
نه دقيقا
You blew up my car. I really loved that car.
تو ماشينم رو منفجر كردي من عاشق اون ماشين بودم
Sorry to hear about that.
از شنيدنش متاسفم
Tremors are getting pretty bad.
لرزش بدنت خيلي بد شده
How are the hallucinations?
توهماتت طور هستن؟
DOLORES: Get out of here, Teddy. This place is gonna be the end of you.
... فرار كن، تدي اينجا قراره آخر خط تو باشه
Not bad.
بد نيست
-They'll get worse. -TEDDY: I know.
اونها بدتر ميشن - ميدونم -
Dr. Solando, she told me about the neuroleptics.
دكتر سولاندو اون به من درباره "نروليتك" توضيح داده
Did she, now? And when was this?
الان بهت فت؟ كِي بهت فت؟
I found her, Doctor, in a cave out by the cliffs.
من يداش كردم دكتر، در يه غار روي صخرهها
-But you'll never get to her. -I don't doubt it,
ولي شما نميتونين بهش برسين - شك ندارم -
considering she's not real.
توهمات تو واقعي نيستن
Your delusions are more severe than I thought.
اما جديتر از اون يزي هستن كه فكر ميكردم
You're not on neuroleptics.
تو تحت " نروليتك" نيستي
You're not on anything, as a matter of fact.
در واقع تو تحت " نروليتك" نيستي
Then what the fuck is this? Huh? What the fuck is this?
اين يه؟ اين لعنتي يه؟
Withdrawal.
صرفنظر كردن
Withdrawal? From what?
صرفنظر كردن؟
I haven't had a goddamn drink since I've been on this island.
از ي؟ من حتي يه نوشيدني هم توي اين جزيره لعنتي نخوردم
Chlorpromazine.
از كلروومازين
I'm not a fan of pharmacology, but I have to say, in your case...
من زياد علاقهاي به دارودرماني ندارم ولي ... در مورد شما
-(STAMMERING) Chloraproma-what? -Chlorpromazine.
كلروو... ي؟ - كلروومازين
The same thing we've been giving you for the past 24 months.
همون يزي كه در 24 ماه ذشته بهت ميداديم
Oh, so for the past two years, you...
س 2 ساله كه
You've had somebody slipping me drugs in Boston. Is that it?
شما يه نفر در بوستون دارين كه به من دارو ميده
Not Boston.
نه در بوستون
Here.
اينجا
You've been here for two years. A patient of this institution.
تو 2 ساله كه اينجايي يكي از بيمارهاي اينجا
After everything I've seen here, Doctor,
بعد از اين همه يزهايي كه اينجا ديدم، دكتر
you really think you're gonna convince me I'm crazy, huh?
واقعا فكر كردي ميتوني منو قانع كني كه ديوانهام؟
Do you know the kind of people that I deal with every day?
تو ميدوني من هر روز با ه آدمهايي سرو كار دارم؟
I'm a U.S. Marshal, for God's sakes.
من يه مارشال هستم
You were a U.S. Marshal.
تو يه مارشال بودي
Here's a copy of the intake form you broke into Ward C for.
اينجا يه كي از فرم ذيرش توئه بردنC تو رو به ساختون
Proof of the 67th patient.
بعنوان بيمار 67 ام
If you'd gotten it to the mainland,
اه تو به سرزمين اصلي برسي
you could have blown the lid off this place.
ميتوني كل اينجا رو نابود كني
-Wait. Where did... Where did you... -Yet somehow,
صبر كن... صبر كن - ... يه جورايي -
you couldn't find time to look at it. Well, read it now.
اما هنوز فرصت نكردي كه بخونيش بير و بخونش
Go ahead.
ادامه بده
"Patient is highly intelligent, highly delusional decorated Army veteran.
بيمار بسيار باهوش و دار توهم شديد است به خودش نشانهاي ليس و ارتش وصل ميكند
(STAMMERING) "Present for the liberation of Dachau.
هنام آزاد كردن " دااو" حضور داشته
"Former U.S. Marshal. Known proclivity for violence.
مارشال سابق ايالات متحده تمايل شديد به خشونت
"Shows no remorse for his crime because he denies the crime ever...
اصلا احساس شيماني نسبت به كاري كه كرده نداره، ون طوري آن جنايت را
"Ever took place.
انكار ميكند، انار اصلا رخ نداده است
"Highly developed and fantastical narratives,
آنقدر خوب و فوقالعاده داستانش رو تعريف ميكند
"which preclude facing the truth of his actions."
كه باعث ... ميشود حقيقت را نبيند
I've had enough of this bullshit! Where's my partner, huh?
از اين مزخرفات خسته شدم همكار من كجاست؟ هان؟
Where's Chuck? Where is he?
اك كجاست؟ اون كجاست؟
Let's try this another way.
بيا روش ديهاي رو امتحان كنيم
Your wife's maiden name was Chanal, am I correct?
اسم وسط همسرت "انا" بود، درست ميم؟
Don't you even talk about her. Don't you...
!حتي اسم اون رو هم نيار
I'm afraid I have to.
متاسفانه بايد بيارم
Notice anything these four names have in common?
متوجه تشابهات اين 4 اسم شدي؟
It's your rule of four.
قانون 4
Andrew, what do you see?
آندرو ي ميبيني؟
If you've done anything to my partner, Doctor, that is a violation of...
اه بلايي سر همكارم بيارين ... دكتر، اين جنايت
Focus, Andrew! What do you see?
تمركز كن، آندرو، ي ميبيني؟
The names have the same letters.
اسامي حروف يكساني دارن
Edward Daniels has exactly the same 13 letters as Andrew Laeddis.
ادوارد دانيلز دقيقا 13 حرف داره مثل آندرو ليديس
The same as Rachel Solando and Dolores Chanal.
همينطور راشل سولاندو و دلور انا. همه اسامي
The names are anagrams for each other.
همه تركيبي از يه سري حروفن
Your tactics, they're not gonna work on me.
اين روشها روي من موثر نيست
You came here for the truth. Here it is.
تو براي حقيقت به اينجا اومدي بيا اينجاست
Your name is Andrew Laeddis.
"اسم تو "آندرو ليديسه
The 67th patient at Ashecliffe is you, Andrew.
بيمار 67 ام اشكليف تويي آندرو
Bullshit.
مزخرفه
You were committed here by court order 24 months ago.
تو 24 ماه قبل به دستور داداه به اينجا فرستاده شدي
Your crime is terrible, one you can't forgive yourself for,
جرمت وحشتناك بود آننان كه نميتونستي خودتو ببخشي
so you invented another self.
س يكي ديه به جاي خودت ساختي
All right.
بسيار خب
(STAMMERING) Let's get down to the facts, all right?
بريم سراغ حقايق
You've created a story in which you're not a murderer.
تو يه داستاني ساختي كه توش تو قاتل نيستي
You're a hero, still a U.S. Marshal, only here at Ashecliffe because of a case,
تو يه قهرماني و يه مارشال ايالتي هستي و بخاطر يه رونده به آشكليف اومدي
and you've uncovered a conspiracy
و توطئهاي رو كشف كردي
so that anything we tell you about who you are, what you've done,
س هريزي كه ما بهت مييم كه كي هستي و يكار كردي
you can dismiss as lies, Andrew.
را دروغ فرض ميكني، آندرو
My name is Edward Daniels.
اسم من ادوارد دانيلزه
I've been hearing this fantasy for two years now. I know every detail.
من 2 ساله كه دارم اين داستان رو ميشنوم همه جزيياتش رو بلدم
Patient 67, the storm,
بيمار 67. طوفان
Rachel Solando, your missing partner, the dreams you have every night.
راشل سولاندو، همكار م شدهات خوابهايي كه هر شب ميبيني
You were at Dachau, but you may not have killed any guards.
تو در دااو بودي ولي هيكس رو نكشتي
I wish I could let you just live in your fantasy world.
آرزو دارم كه ميذاشتم در دنياي خياليات زندي كني
I really do.
واقعا اميدوار هستم
But you're violent, trained, dangerous.
اما تو خشن هستي، خطرناكي
You're the most dangerous patient we have.
تو خطرناكترين بيمار اينجايي
You've injured orderlies, guards, other patients.
تو به همه نهبانها صدمه زدي، به بقيه بيمارها
Two weeks ago, you attacked George Noyce.
دو هفته يش به جرج نويس حمله كردي
No, no. I am fucking on to you, Doctor.
نه، نه، من كاري باهاش نداشتم
-You had Noyce beaten. -Of course I didn't!
تو به نويس صدمه زدي - البته كه نين كاري نكردم -
Give me one reason why I would even touch him!
يه دليل بيار كه را حتي من بهش دست بزنم
Because he called you Laeddis,
ون اون بهت فته بود ليديس
and you'd do anything not to be him.
و تو هركاري ميكني كه اون نباشي
I have a transcript of the conversation you had with Noyce yesterday.
من متن فتوي ديروز تو و نويس رو دارم
"This is about you, and, Laeddis, that's all it's ever been about."
اين درباره تو و ليديسه يزي كه هميشه بوده
No, no. He's saying this is about me and Laeddis.
نه، نه "اون ميه اين درباره "من و ليديسه
When you asked him what happened to his face,
وقتي تو ازش رسيدي ه بلايي سر صورتت اومده
he said, now here I'm quoting again, "You did this."
اون ميه، بيا اينجا نوشته "تو اين كارو كردي"
No, no, he meant that it was my fault.
... نه، اون فت كه اين تقصير من بوده كه
You almost killed him.
تو داشتي اونو ميكشتي
The warden and the Board of Overseers are determined something be done.
زندانبان و مسئولين اينجا تصميمشونو رفتن
It's been decided
تصميم رفته شده
that unless we can bring you back to sanity now,
با اينحال ما ميتونيم ديوانيت رو درمان كنيم
right now,
همين حالا
permanent measures will be taken to ensure you can't hurt anyone ever again.
و مطمئن بشيم كه ديه نميتوني به كسي آزار برسوني
They'll lobotomize you, Andrew. Do you understand?
اونها قسمتي از مغزت رو خارج ميكنن، آندرو ميفهمي؟
Yeah, I understand.
بله، ميفهمم
I understand just fine.
خيلي خوب ميفهمم
If I don't play along with your little game here,
اه ... اه من نتونم از س بازي كوولوي شما بربيام
Dr. Naehring's gonna turn me into one of his ghosts.
دكتر نرين منو به يكي از روحهاش تبديل ميكنه
But what about my partner?
همكارم ي؟
You gonna tell the U.S. Marshal's office that he's a defense mechanism?
شما مييد كه يه مارشال ايالتي هم جز توهمات منه؟
Hello, boss.
سلام رييس
(SOFTLY) What the fuck is going on here? Hmm?
اينجا ه خبره؟
Huh?
هان؟
You working for him?
تو براي اون كار ميكني؟
I'm sorry. There wasn't any other way.
متاسفم، اره ديهاي نداشتيم
Someone had to stick with you, keep you safe.
ولي يكي بايد يش تو ميموند و ازت مراقبت ميكرد
You been watching me, huh?
تو مراقب من بودي، نه؟
Watching me every minute.
هميشه مراقبم بودي
Who are you?
تو... تو كي هستي؟
Who are you? Tell me.
تو كي هستي؟ بهم بو
Don't you recognize me, Andrew?
منو يادت نمياد، آندرو؟
I've been your primary psychiatrist for the last two years.
من روانشناس اصلي تو بودم در اين 2 سال ذشته
I'm Lester Sheehan.
من "لستر شيهان" هستم
-I told you... I told you about my wife, I... -I know.
... و من درباره زنم باهات صحبت كردم
I climbed down a cliff to get you. I trusted you.
ميدونم - من از يه صخره بالا رفتم كه نجاتت بدم
I risked everything to come in here after you. Everything!
من بهت اعتماد كردم. من همه يزم !رو بخاطر تو به خطر انداختم، همه يزم رو
-I know, boss. -We're running out of time here, Andrew.
ميدونم، رييس - وقتمون داره تموم ميشه، آندرو -
I swore before the Board of Overseers
من به همه مسئولين اينجا قول داده بودم كه
that I could construct the most radical, cutting-edge role-play
به بهترين وجه ممكني كه در تاريخ روانشناسي
ever attempted in psychiatry, and it would bring you back.
كسي نقش بازي كرده نقش بازي كنم تا تو حالت خوب بشه
I thought that if we let you play this out
من فكر كردم اه تو اين بازي رو ادامه بدي
we could get you to see how untrue, how impossible it is.
خواهي فهميد كه قدر نادرست و غيرممكنه
You've had the run of the place for two days.
ما مجبور شديم دو روز روي اينجا كار كنيم
Tell me, where are the Nazi experiments?
بهم بو اون خاطراتت از نازيها از كجا اومدن
The satanic ORs?
اتاقهاي عمل شيطاني
Andrew, listen to me.
آندرو، به حرفهام وش كن
If we fail with you,
ار در مورد تو شكست بخوريم
then everything that we've tried to do here will be discredited. Everything.
تمام كارهايي كه اينجا ميكنيم، زير سوال ميره همه كارها
We're on the front lines of a war here, old boy.
ما در خط مقدم يه جنيم، آندرو
And right now, it all comes down to you.
و الان همه يز به تو وابسته است
-Don't move! Don't move! -Andrew! Andrew! No. No.
!حركت نكنين - !آندرو، نه -
(ENUNCIATING) My name is Edward Daniels!
!اسم من ادوارد دانيلزه
This one's loaded. I can tell by the weight.
اين يكي اسلحه ره از روي وزنش ميم
I see. And that's your firearm, Marshal? You're sure?
ميبينم و اين اسلحه توئه مارشال؟ مطمئني؟
My initials are on the side.
امضام روشه
There's a dent in the barrel from when Philip Stacks shot at me.
يه فرورفتي روي لولهي اسلحه من بود از روزي كه "فيلي استاك"به من شليك كرد
You're not gonna fuck with my mind on this one, Doctor!
و لولهاش كمونه كرد، نميتونين با اين حرفها ولم بزنين
CAWLEY: Then blast away.
س شليك كن
Because that's the only way you're ever getting off this island.
ون تنها راه حل ممكن براي تو براي خروج از اين جزيرست
Andrew, please don't.
آندرو، خواهش ميكنم اين كارو نكن
My gun.
اسلحهام
What did you do to my goddamn gun?
با اسلحهام يكار كردين
It's a toy, Andrew.
اون يه اسباببازيه آندرو
We're telling you the truth.
ما حقيقت رو بهت مييم
Dolores was insane, manic-depressive, suicidal.
دلورس رواني بود، افسردي رواني داشت تمايل به خودكشي
You drank, stayed away, ignored what everyone told you.
تو هم الكلي بودي، به يزهايي كه ديران بهت ميفتن توجه نميكردي
You moved to that lake house
شما به اون خونه كنار درياه رفتين
after she purposely set your city apartment on fire.
بعد از اينكه اون عمدا آارتمانتون رو آتش زد
-You were... -(SCREAMING) You're lying!
... شماها - !دروغ ميي -
-Andrew! Andrew, stop. No. -You drugged the cigarettes!
آندرو... آندرو! بس كن - !شماها سيارها رو مسموم كردين -
-All you've done is lie! -Andrew. Andrew.
!شماها دروغ ميين - آندرو، آندرو -
Your children. Andrew, your children.
اينها بههاي تو هستن
Simon. Henry.
سايمون، هنري
I never had any children.
من بهاي ندارم
Your wife drowned them at the cabin by the lake.
همسرت اونها رو خفه كرد در درياه كنار خونهتون
And here, the little girl, the one you dream of
و اين دختري كه خوابش رو ميبيني
every night.
هر شب
I never had a little girl.
من دختري ندارم
The one who tells you over and over that you should have saved her,
همون دختري كه همش بهت ميه بايد نجاتش بدي
saved them all.
همشون رو نجات بدي
Your daughter, her name was Rachel.
... دخترت اسمش راشله
Are you going to deny that she ever lived?
ميخواي بي اون هيوقت زندي نميكرده؟
Andrew, are you?
آندرو؟ اينو ميي؟
DOLORES: (WHIMPERING) I'm so sorry, baby.
واقعا متاسفم، عزيزم
I told you not to come in here.
بهت كه فتم به اينجا نيا
I told you this would be the end of you.
بهت فته بودم اينجا آخر خط توئه
I'm back!
من برشتم
We got him just outside of Oklahoma.
ما بيرون اوكلاهوما رفتميش
Must've stopped 10 places in between here and Tulsa.
بين اينجا و تولسا در ده جا وايساديم
I could sleep for a week.
حالا ميتونم براي يه هفته بخوابم
Dolores?
دلورس؟
PREACHER: And he said, "Take up your bed and walk." But God?
و اون فت، بلند شو و راه برو !اما خدايا؟
Dolores?
دلورس؟
PREACHER: Then he said, "Take up your bed and walk."
بعد او فت بلند شو و راه برو
Forgive sins, but God?
ناهان رو ببخش !اما خدايا؟
Dolores?
دلورس؟
Baby,
... عزيزم
why are you all wet?
را لباسهات خيسه؟
I missed you.
دلم برات تن شده بود
I wanna go home.
ميخوام برردم خونه
You are home.
تو الان در خونهاي
Where are the kids?
بهها كجان؟
Hmm?
هان؟
They're in school.
رفتن مدرسه
It's Saturday, honey.
امروز شنبه است عزيزم
School's not in on Saturday.
مدرسهها شنبه تعطيلن
My school is.
مدرسه من بازه
Oh, my God.
!خداي من
Oh, my God, no.
!خداي من! نه
Come on, come on.
!بجنب
No. No. Please, God.
!خواهش ميكنم، خدايا! نه
Please, God, no!
!خداي من! نه
No!
!!!!نــــه
No.
!نه
Baby.
عزيزم
Let's put them at the table, Andrew.
بيا ببريمشون توي آشزخونه
We'll dry them off. We'll change their clothes.
خشكشون ميكنيم لباسهاشون رو عوض ميكنيم
They'll be our living dolls. Huh?
اونها عروسكهاي زنده ما ميشن
Tomorrow we can take them on a picnic.
فردا ميبريمشون ردش
If you ever loved me, Dolores,
اه منو دوست داري، دلورس
please stop talking.
ديه حرفي نزن
I love you.
دوستت دارم
Set me free.
منو راحت كن
Oh, baby.
عزيزم
We'll give them baths.
ما ميبريمشون حمام
-I love you, baby. -I love you, too.
دوستت دارم عزيزم - منم دوستت دارم -
-I love you so much.
خيلي دوستت دارم - ... دوستت دارم، دوستت دارم -
I love you. I...
دوستت دارم
(SOBBING) Oh, baby.
... عزيزم
Andrew.
... آندرو
Andrew, can you hear me?
آندرو، صدامو ميشنوي؟
Rachel. Rachel, Rachel.
راشل! راشل، راشل
Rachel?
راشل؟
Rachel who?
راشل ي؟
Rachel. Rachel Laeddis.
راشل. راشل ليديس
My daughter.
دخترم
Why are you here?
را تو اينجا هستي؟
Because I killed my wife.
ون همسرم رو كشتم
And why did you do that?
و را اين كارو كردي؟
Because she murdered our children,
اون بههامون رو كشته بود
and she told me to let her go.
و ازم خواست راحتش كنم
-Who's Teddy Daniels? -He doesn't exist.
تدي دانيلز كيه؟ - نين كسي وجود نداره -
Neither does Rachel Solando. I made them up.
همينطور راشل سولاندو من اين اسمها رو ساختم
-Why? -CAWLEY: We need to hear you say it.
را؟ - بايد از زبان خودت بشنويم -
After she tried to kill herself the first time,
بعد از اينكه براي بار اول سعي كرد خودكشي كنه
Dolores told me she...
دلورس بهم فت
She had an insect living inside her brain.
... ميفت يه حشره توي مغزش زندي ميكنه
She could feel it clicking across her skull,
اون احساس ميكرد كه در اطراف جمجمهاش حركت ميكنه
just pulling the wires just for fun.
و براي تفريح، اعصابش رو تحريك ميكنه
She told me that.
اون بهم فت
She told me that, but I didn't listen.
اون بهم فت ولي من توجهي نكردم
I loved her so much, you know.
من خيلي دوستش داشتم
CAWLEY: Why did you make them up?
را اين اسامي رو ساختي؟
Because I can't take knowing that Dolores killed our children.
ون نميتونستم قبول كنم، دلورس بههامون رو كشته
And I...
... و من
I killed them 'cause I didn't get her help, you know.
من اونها رو كشتم، ون نتونستم به زنم كمك كنم
I killed them.
..من اونها رو كشتم
Here's my fear, Andrew.
من ميترسم، آندرو
We broke through once before, nine months ago,
يه بار ديه هم اين اتفاق افتاده. نه ماه يش
and then you regressed.
و بعدش دوباره مريضيت برشت
-I don't remember that. -I know.
يادم نمياد - ميدونم -
You reset, Andrew.
تو ريست شدي آندرو
Like a tape playing over and over on an endless loop.
مثل يه نوار كه دوباره خش بشه بارها و بارها، در يه رخش دايم
I hope that what we've done here will be enough
اميدوار بودم كارهايي كه ميكنيم باعث بشه
to stop it from ever happening again,
ديه اين اتفاق تكرار نشه
but I need to know you've accepted reality.
ار ه، من بايد بدونم كه تو واقعيت رو قبول كردي
You came after me, huh, Doctor?
تو اومدي دنبالم دكتر؟
You tried to help me when no one else would.
تو سعي كردي كمكم كني وقتي هيكسي نميخواست
My name's Andrew Laeddis,
اسم من آندرو ليديسه
and I murdered my wife in the spring of '52.
و من همسرم رو در بهار 1952 كشتم
How we doing this morning?
امروز حالت طوره؟
-Good. And you? -Can't complain.
خوبم. تو طوري؟ - شكايتي ندارم -
So what's our next move?
قدم بعدي يه؟
You tell me.
تو بو
We gotta get off this rock, Chuck.
من از اين جزيره ميرم بيرون، اك
Get back to the mainland.
برميردم به سرزمين اصلي
Whatever the hell's going on here, it's bad.
هريزي كه اينجا ميذره خيلي بده
(WHISPERING) Don't worry, partner, they're not gonna catch us.
نران نباش همكار اونها نميتونن مارو بيرن
That's right. We're too smart for them.
ما خيلي از اونها باهوشتريم
Yeah, we are, aren't we?
آره، درسته، مه نه؟
You know, this place makes me wonder...
ميدوني، اينجا منو به فكر فرو ميبره
Yeah, what's that, boss?
ه فكري رييس؟
Which would be worse,
كدوم بدتره؟
to live as a monster
...زندي كردن مثل يك هيولا
or to die as a good man?
.يا مردن مثل يك مرد خوب
Teddy?
تدي؟